<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fatal jealousie a tragedy acted at the Duke's Theatre.</title>
            <author>Payne, Henry Neville, fl. 1672-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56731</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13790742</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13790742</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56731)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 470:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fatal jealousie a tragedy acted at the Duke's Theatre.</title>
                  <author>Payne, Henry Neville, fl. 1672-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 74, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Dring ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ascribed to Payne.  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed Novemb. 22, 1672; Roger L'Estrange."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101837:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Fatal Jealouſie.</p>
            <p>A TRAGEDY.</p>
            <p>Acted at the Duke's Theatre.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license_to_print">
                        <p>Licenſed</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Novemb.</hi> 22, 1672.</date>
                           <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Dring,</hi> at the
<hi>White Lyon,</hi> next <hi>Chancery-Lane</hi> end in
<hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:101837:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div n="men" type="dramatis_personae">
               <head>The Actors Names.</head>
               <list>
                  <label>Don Antonio. <hi>A Jealous Lord.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Smith.</item>
                  <label>Don Gerardo. <hi>Friend to</hi> Antonio.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Medburn.</item>
                  <label>Don Franciſco. A <hi>Young Lord.</hi>
                  </label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Young.</item>
                  <label>Don Sebaſtian. <hi>Friend to</hi> Franciſco.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Crosby.</item>
                  <label>Jaſper. A <hi>Villain. Servant to</hi> Antonio.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Sandford.</item>
                  <label>Pedro. <hi>Servant to</hi> Antonio.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Burford.</item>
                  <label>Servant <hi>To</hi> Gerardo.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Norris.</item>
                  <label>Captain of the Watch. </label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Nath. Leigh.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>Souldiers. </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="women" type="dramatis_personae">
               <head>Women.</head>
               <list>
                  <label>Caelia. <hi>Wife to</hi> Antonio.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Shadwel.</item>
                  <label>Eugenia. <hi>Siſter to</hi> Caelia.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Betterton.</item>
                  <label>Flora. <hi>Waiting Woman to</hi> Caelia.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Osborn.</item>
                  <label>Nurſe <hi>To</hi> Caelia.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Nokes.</item>
                  <label>Witch. <hi>Aunt to</hi> Jaſper.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Norris.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>Spirits.</item>
                  <item>Gipſies.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:101837:2"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE</head>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>TO you, great Sovereign Wits, that have ſuch ſway,</l>
               <l>Without Controul to ſave, or damn a Play;</l>
               <l>That with a piſh, my Anthony, or ſo,</l>
               <l>Can the beſt Rally'd ſence at once or'e throw;</l>
               <l>And by this pow'r, that none muſt queſtion now,</l>
               <l>Have made the moſt Rebellious Writers bow,</l>
               <l>Our Author, here his low Submiſſion brings,</l>
               <l>Begging your paſs, calls you the Stages Kings;</l>
               <l>He ſayes, nay, on a Play-Book, ſwears it too,</l>
               <l>Your pox uppo'nt damn it, what's here to do?</l>
               <l>Your nods, your winks, nay, your leaſt ſigns of Wit,</l>
               <l>Are truer Reaſon than e're Poet writ,</l>
               <l>And he obſerves do much more ſway the Pit.</l>
               <l>For ſitting there h'has ſeen the leſſer gang</l>
               <l>Of Callow Criticks down their heads to bang;</l>
               <l>Lending long Ears to all that you ſhould ſay,</l>
               <l>So underſtand, yet never hear the Play:</l>
               <l>Then in the Tavern ſwear their time they've loſt,</l>
               <l>And Curſe the Poet put e'm to that coſt.</l>
               <l>And if one would their juſt Exceptions know,</l>
               <l>They heard ſuch, ſuch, or ſuch a one ſay ſo;</l>
               <l>And thus in time by your diſlikes they riſe,</l>
               <l>To be thought Judges, though indeed but ſpyes.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:101837:3"/>
               <l>This is not fair your Subjects to betray</l>
               <l>To thoſe that ſtrive to Rival you in ſway;</l>
               <l>That will in time by your expence of wit,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp or'e us, and your ſucceſſors ſit.</l>
               <l>Theſe and ſome other dangers to remove,</l>
               <l>We beg that though this Play you diſapprove,</l>
               <l>Say nothing of it here, and when you're gone,</l>
               <l>We give that leave you'le take to cry it down;</l>
               <l>Thus you preſerve your pow'r, and we ſhall be</l>
               <l>From Fopps, and Demi-Criticks Cenſure free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Subdu'd by force, we Tyrants thus obey,</l>
               <l>But Ladys, you like lawful Monarches ſway,</l>
               <l>You Rule by Love, and Pardon faults with eaſe,</l>
               <l>In Subjects that do all they can to pleaſe.</l>
               <l>By faction they condemn, you by our Peers;</l>
               <l>And he is guilty ſure ſuch Trial fears:</l>
               <l>And though our Author pleads not guilty now.</l>
               <l>And to his Tryal ſtands, he hopes that you,</l>
               <l>Will not too ſtrictly his accuſers hear,</l>
               <l>For if this Play can draw from you a Tear,</l>
               <l>He'l ſlight the Wits, Half-Wits, and Criticks too;</l>
               <l>And Judge his ſtrength by his well pleaſing you.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101837:3"/>
            <head>THE Fatal Jealouſie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Act the Firſt. Scene the Firſt.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>The Curtain drawn Diſcovers</hi> Don Antonio
<hi>and</hi> Caelia <hi>in Morning-Gowns. Chamber and Bed.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>MY Lord, you well may blame my conduct of that bus'neſs,</l>
                  <l>Since it produc'd ſuch diſmal Accidents,</l>
                  <l>As my heart trembles but to think upon;</l>
                  <l>Yet for <hi>Don Lewis</hi>'s Innocence and mine,</l>
                  <l>In the contrivance of that Fatal Meeting;</l>
                  <l>I muſt for ever, during Life, be Champion.</l>
                  <l>And, as he with his dying breath proteſted,</l>
                  <l>He ne're meant wrong to you; ſo am I ready</l>
                  <l>To dye a Martyr to my Innocence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come, theſe are but wyles to Palliate things,</l>
                  <l>Can you believe me ſtupid, or an Aſs?</l>
                  <l>To think my Wife ſhould meet a Man i'th' Night;</l>
                  <l>Nay, more; a Man that was my ſeeming Friend:</l>
                  <l>Yet taken in at Window privately!</l>
                  <l>Nay, which was moſt, ſtay with him two full hours,</l>
                  <l>And in a Room made proper by a Bed,</l>
                  <l>And yet not Cuckold me; the thing's too plain,</l>
                  <l>I do not doubt the deed, which Iv'e Reveng'd</l>
                  <l>In part, by killing him: No, I am mad,</l>
                  <l>That you ſhould think ſo meanly ſtill of me,</l>
                  <l>As to hope time may alter my belief;</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101837:4"/>
                  <l>Which is by ſuch unerring Reaſons fixt:</l>
                  <l>Or elſe that you ſuſpect my Truth, when I have ſworn</l>
                  <l>By all things ſacred; nay, upon my Honour</l>
                  <l>(Which I am ſo Jealous of) that if you would</l>
                  <l>Relate the truth of your ſo cloſe amours,</l>
                  <l>I from my memory would blot it all,</l>
                  <l>And look on you at worſt, but as the Widdow</l>
                  <l>Of your dead Couzen <hi>Lewis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Good my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Forbear to uſe theſe killing Arguments,</l>
                  <l>Which every moment give me many Deaths,</l>
                  <l>Rather be like your ſelf, that's Gen'rous,</l>
                  <l>And kill me once for all; torment me not</l>
                  <l>By giving no belief, either to Vows</l>
                  <l>Or Actions that have ſpoke my Innocence:</l>
                  <l>Reflect (my Lord) on the unwearied pains</l>
                  <l>Iv'e took to gain your pardon for his Death.</l>
                  <l>Think with what patience I've ſuffer'd ſtill</l>
                  <l>Your often ſtarts of Paſſion, which ſometimes</l>
                  <l>Have ne're produc'd th' effects of Cruelty.</l>
                  <l>And without boaſt, my Lord, you well do know</l>
                  <l>My Friends were much too ſtrong for yours at Court,</l>
                  <l>Then had I but made known your ſevere Carriage,</l>
                  <l>Or ſuffer'd your ſurprizal — 'tis too plain;</l>
                  <l>Yoor Life had been a forfeit to the Law.</l>
                  <l>And were I but the wanton Wife you think me,</l>
                  <l>What wou'd more welcome be then that Revenge —</l>
                  <l>Here on my knees I beg again, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>You would perſwade your ſelf, that what I told you</l>
                  <l>Was cauſe of that cloſe meeting, was ſo truly,</l>
                  <l>And no invention; and as this Day</l>
                  <l>Began our Nuptial Joys, ſo let it end</l>
                  <l>Our Marriage Diſcords; then ſhall I have cauſe</l>
                  <l>To keep it Annually a Feſtival;</l>
                  <l>In thanks to Heav'n for two ſuch mighty Bleſſings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caelia,</hi> ſtand up, I will perſwade my ſelf.</l>
                  <l>By this — I will as much as e're I can,</l>
                  <stage>Kiſſes her.</stage>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101837:4"/>
                  <l>That thou art Innocent, for if thou bee'ſt not,</l>
                  <l>What Woman in the World ought to be thought ſo?</l>
                  <l>But prethee be diſcreet, mannage thy Actions</l>
                  <l>With ſtricteſt Rules of Prudence, for if not,</l>
                  <l>Like to a Bow or'e-bent, I ſhall ſtart back,</l>
                  <l>And break with paſſion on thee: wilt thou be careful?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh! I am paid for all my ſufferings,</l>
                  <l>This kindneſs does or'e-joy me, which, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Let me for ever loſe when any Act</l>
                  <l>Of mine, ſhall juſtly make a forfeit of it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Flora.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, here's <hi>Don Gerardo</hi> come to ſee you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Admit him in.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Flora.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>I will retire, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>You need not, <hi>Caelia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Gerardo.</stage>
                  <l>Welcome, <hi>Gerardo,</hi> this is like a Friend,</l>
                  <l>That name ſhould know no Ceremonious Laws,</l>
                  <l>Let them make formal Viſits that maintain,</l>
                  <l>As formal Friendſhips; ours is try'd and true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gerar.</speaker>
                  <l>This, as I take it, was your Wedding-day,</l>
                  <l>At which (your pardon, Madam, for a truth.)</l>
                  <l>I was a Jealous waiter; your great worth</l>
                  <l>Made me to fear I then had loſt a Friend,</l>
                  <l>And in that room ſhould an acquaintance find.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>But now, my Lord, you ſee how you miſtook,</l>
                  <l>I was a Rival to his Miſtreſſes,</l>
                  <l>But to his Friends, one to increaſe their number.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>I find the truth ſo great, I wiſh you may</l>
                  <l>Live long and happy to poſſeſs that place;</l>
                  <l>Yet I'le confeſs I did not loſe my fears,</l>
                  <l>Till my dear Friend was pleas'd to uſe my Sword,</l>
                  <l>As Second, in the Quarrel with your Kinſman,</l>
                  <l>The Unfortunate <hi>Don Lewis;</hi> and I proteſt</l>
                  <l>Such Joy I met to be employ'd by him,</l>
                  <l>That I ne're ſought to know what caus'd the quarrel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I beg your pardon,</l>
                  <l>I have ſome little bus'neſs in my Cloſet</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101837:5"/>
                  <l>Which forces me retire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Lady looks as if ſhe were diſpleas'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>That Kinſman whom I ſlew is never nam'd,</l>
                  <l>But if ſhe hears it ſhe avoids the place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm troubled much to be th' occaſion now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter, Friend, ſhe only knows the cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Why from ſuch Friendſhip we grew Enemies,</l>
                  <l>And there is reaſon why ſhe ſhould be griev'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>That ſudden and ſo ſecret Quarrel</l>
                  <l>Did much amaze all <hi>Naples;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And I (as Actor in it) often have been preſt</l>
                  <l>To tell the cauſe, which yet I never could.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>No, Friend, nor never muſt:</l>
                  <l>The Gen'rous <hi>Lewis;</hi> ſo I'le call him now,</l>
                  <l>Since he ſo bravely dy'd, was alwayes juſt</l>
                  <l>During that little time he breath'd this Air;</l>
                  <l>After his mortal Wound, for he Related</l>
                  <l>A Story of it fitted us for pardon:</l>
                  <l>Yet never told that Secret, only known</l>
                  <l>On Earth, to him, to <hi>Caelia,</hi> and my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>I'me not inquiſitive, nor never was,</l>
                  <l>There may be ſecrets fit for no Mans hearing.</l>
                  <l>And 'tis an Act of Friendſhip full as great.</l>
                  <l>To tell a Friend I hide a ſecret from him,</l>
                  <l>As to Relate it, ſince they both ſhew Candor —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Happy <hi>Antonio,</hi> in a Friend ſo juſt!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Happy <hi>Gerardo,</hi> rather, that can ſay</l>
                  <l>He's ſure he has a Friend, that dares employ him;</l>
                  <l>For confidence in Friends makes Friendſhip ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>And deareſt Friend, I'le not doubt yours ſo much,</l>
                  <l>To think you would not uſe this Life of mine,</l>
                  <l>As 'twere your own in any thing concerns you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Ne're doubt it, Friend, I ſoon ſhall find occaſion</l>
                  <l>Boldly to uſe the power, and to ſpeak truth;</l>
                  <l>My coming now was chiefly to that purpoſe;</l>
                  <l>Though I intended to ſpend this day too</l>
                  <l>In Recreation with you, and to ſee you Bedded,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101837:5"/>
                  <l>Like a new Bride and Bride-groom,</l>
                  <l>Then wiſhing you long: long and laſting Joys,</l>
                  <l>Retire, and wiſh to Copy out your Life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Has <hi>Don Gerardo</hi> Service for <hi>Antonio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His own <hi>Antonio,</hi> and yet defers to name it?</l>
                  <l>Speak your Commands, that I as ſwift may flye</l>
                  <l>To put 'em into Action, as I did</l>
                  <l>At firſt to meet thoſe pleaſures Lovers long for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>My fears perſwade me I ſhall ſpeak too ſoon,</l>
                  <l>Yet dreſs your ſelf, and come into the Garden,</l>
                  <l>I with impatience there will wait to tell you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Go then, you ſhall not long be ſilent.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Gerardo.</stage>
                  <l>Who waits there?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pedro, <hi>and Exit.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro,</hi> call my Wife —</l>
                  <l>My Wife, ſaid I! <hi>Gerardo,</hi> didſt thou know</l>
                  <l>The ſecret fears contain'd within this Boſome,</l>
                  <l>Thou'dſt ſooner pitty me, than wiſh my Life:</l>
                  <l>How can I think her ſtory of the Jewels,</l>
                  <l>And other matters 'bout her Fathers Will,</l>
                  <l>Could have produc'd ſo ſcandalous a Meeting?</l>
                  <l>And yet ſhe ſtill avows it! Oh, Jealouſie!</l>
                  <l>Where will theſe panting fears ſtill hurry me?</l>
                  <l>I hourly ſeek to find what I wou'd give,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand Worlds my heart would ne're believe;</l>
                  <l>And yet for what do I thus vex my ſelf?</l>
                  <l>For that, which if 'twas gone, I cou'd not miſs;</l>
                  <l>No, would I could, for then I'de never fear,</l>
                  <l>But when I found her Honour gone aſtray,</l>
                  <l>I'd ſend her Life to fetch mine back again.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Caelia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>What's your Command, my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee, my Dear, do not retire too much,</l>
                  <l>But ſhew a merry freedom to our Friends,</l>
                  <l>That they may think us happy, themſelves welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I ſhall, and reaſon have to do it;</l>
                  <l>But I deſire you would diſpence my abſence,</l>
                  <l>Only a little time, I being preparing</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101837:6"/>
                  <l>A general Confeſſion I ſhall make to Morrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>You'l be too long about it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>No, my Lord, I take the ſhorteſt way</l>
                  <l>In writing what my thoughts can re-collect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <p>You would not let me read it, when y'have done?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>I do confeſs I ſhould be loath, my Lord.</l>
                  <l>But yet from any Sin concerns your ſelf,</l>
                  <l>I am as free as are the purer Angels,</l>
                  <l>Or may I find no profit by my Prayers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I will believe thee; go, make haſte and do it.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Caelia.</stage>
                  <l>Yet, if't be poſſible, I'm reſolv'd to ſee it;</l>
                  <l>'Tvvill Cure my fears, perhaps, or change their Natures,</l>
                  <l>And make 'em certainties the leſſer evil cauſe ſooner Cur'd:</l>
                  <l>For Jealouſies with fear doth plague the mind,</l>
                  <l>But that is Cur'd when certainties we find.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Anto.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>The Scene changes, Diſcovers</hi> Jaſper, <hi>as from Bed, Buttoning himſelf.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, plague o'this Old Bitch, ſhe has kept me</l>
                  <l>So awake with her Coughing all Night, that I</l>
                  <l>Have quite out-ſlept my ſelf.</l>
                  <stage>Looks on's Watch.</stage>
                  <l>By Heav'n near Ten a Clock, and ſhe not gone</l>
                  <l>Yet — plague on her — ſhe'l be catch'd, and I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be turn'd away — why Nurſe — make haſte, 'tis Ten a</l>
                  <l>Clock and paſt, you will be wanting.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe within.</speaker>
                  <l>That cannot be, alas, the times but ſhort</l>
                  <l>That I've been with thee, my Dear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>No, perhaps you think ſo;</l>
                  <l>But let me ever want money to drink,</l>
                  <l>If I have not thought the time longer</l>
                  <l>Then her Life has been, and that began beyond the mem'ry</l>
                  <l>Of ma. What drudgery am I forc'd to undergo to</l>
                  <l>Get a little money to ſupport me — that I may Live to</l>
                  <l>Watch all apted times for my Revenge on this whole</l>
                  <l>Family, who Riſe upon the Ruines of our Houſe.</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101837:6"/>
                  <l>This Nurſe of Ninety never ſtayes with me but I'de as</l>
                  <l>live have been Rid by a Night-Mare.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>What's that, Night-Mate? Am I a Night-Mare?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>No, Nurſe, I ſaid, I was troubl'd with a Night-Mare,</l>
                  <l>And ſhould be worſe, were it not for thy Company.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I am good Friend of thine every way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>That's true; but Nurſe make haſte, for I am</l>
                  <l>Damnably afraid <hi>Flora</hi> ſuſpects us e're ſince</l>
                  <l>She took me in your Chamber, and if ſhe ſhou'd</l>
                  <l>Take you here, and tell my Lady, I ſhould be turn'd</l>
                  <l>Away, for you know ſhe loves me not e're ſince I</l>
                  <l>Gave my Lord notice of her meeting <hi>Don Lewis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To give him the money and Jewels, her Father</l>
                  <l>Left privately in her hands for him when he dy'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I Chuck, but why didſt thou do ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>In hopes to have got ſome of the money for my</l>
                  <l>Diſcovery, what made her tempt me with the</l>
                  <l>Truſt of money, and give me none to keep Counſel.</l>
                  <l>But prethee Nurſe be gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I, give me but one buſs, and I will.</p>
                  <stage>Kiſſes him, and is going.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>What a belch was there to perfume it?</p>
                  <stage>She comes back.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet Rogue, I cannot go without the other kiſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, Nurſe! you will undo me; prethee no more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>What, Raſcal, ſlight my favours? you ſhall repent it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Nurſe, think not ſo, but —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flora within.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, Nurſe, Nurſe, my Lady wants you; come away there,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flora within.</speaker>
                  <p>I know where you have been all Night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, there 'tis — this is what I fear'd, I am undone,</l>
                  <l>A plague of Cubbard Love — ſtep into the Cloſet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>What's that you ſay, Cubbard Love?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, prethee no Arguments, but ſtep into the Cloſet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flora within.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, Nurſe, I ſay! why don't you come away?</l>
                  <l>My Lady wants you.</l>
                  <stage>Jaſper <hi>goes to the Door.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flora,</hi> what's the matter with you? Nurſe is not here;</l>
                  <l>Do but come in and ſee.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Flora.</stage>
               </sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101837:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come, ſhe muſt be here; for ſhe</l>
                  <l>was not in her own Bed to Night, and where ſhould</l>
                  <l>She be, but with you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>With me! what the Devil ſhould ſhe do with me?</l>
                  <l>Can't her Old Chopps mumble her Beads o're, but I</l>
                  <l>Muſt keep count of her her <hi>Pater Noſters:</hi> No, no, ſhe's</l>
                  <l>Gon on Pilgrimage to ſome Shrine, to beg Children</l>
                  <l>For my Lady; 'tis a devout Old Woman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Devout! I, her Devotion and yours are much alike,</l>
                  <l>The Fit ne're took you but once in your Lives, and</l>
                  <l>Then, 'tis true you wept at Prayers, that was, at your</l>
                  <l>Own Chriſtnings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee more Charity, ſweet dear <hi>Flora;</hi> come, let</l>
                  <l>Me kiſs thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray forbear, I'de ſooner kiſs a Horſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo ſcornful, dear <hi>Flora?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <p>That's not my bus'neſs; come, tell me, where's the Nurſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee, why doſt ask me for the Nurſe? Doſt think</l>
                  <l>I am ſo hot to make Love to a Monument? Why, ſhe's</l>
                  <l>Old enough to be Mother of all Mankind; her skin's</l>
                  <l>Turn'd to parchment, he that ſhould enjoy her, had as</l>
                  <l>Good lye with a bundle of Old Records. In truth, ſhe's</l>
                  <l>Fit for nothing now, but to be hang'd up amongſt the</l>
                  <l>Monſters in a 'Pothecaries Shop, where, with abuſe to</l>
                  <l>The Beaſt, ſhe would be taken for a large Apes skin ſtufft</l>
                  <l>VVith Hay. Ah, <hi>Flora,</hi> if ſhe were as Young as thou art,</l>
                  <l>then't might be likely, I might find her when ſhe was loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, if ſhe be not here now, I'm ſure it was not for</l>
                  <l>Nothing you once loſt your way into her Chamber,</l>
                  <l>And ſtaid all Night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Meer Drunkenneſs, by this Light, <hi>Flora!</hi> VVhy, if it had</l>
                  <l>Been a Vault full of Dead Carkaſſes, I ſhould have ſlipt</l>
                  <l>Into it in the pickle I was in — Nay, for ought I know,</l>
                  <l>VVith more pleaſure too.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Now out upon you for a Rogue,</l>
                  <l>There's no enduring this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Do but hear me, Nurſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101837:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, hear him, Nurſe, he'l be ſure to recant and</l>
                  <l>Swear you're as ſweet as — a — fogh — ſo ſweet —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat, Huſſy, dare you abuſe me — I that gave ſuck</l>
                  <l>To my Lady before thou waſt born — you Young VVhore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Young VVhore! why not Old VVhore, Nurſe, as well as</l>
                  <l>Young VVhore?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>You damn'd Young Slut, I'le tear out your Eyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>My Feet ſhall ſave my Eyes, except you can out-run</l>
                  <l>Me to my Lady.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Flora.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Have not you made fine work now? I but diſſembled</l>
                  <l>To take off ſuſpition — and you muſt ſhew your ſelf,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure I ſhall be turn'd away for your folly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>But diſſembled, ſaid you? Marry, there's diſſembling indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, Nurſe, conſider, doſt think I would have ſpoke ſo</l>
                  <l>In thy hearing, had it been for any other thing? But</l>
                  <l>Prethee kiſs me — I proteſt thou'rt as ſweet as
<hi>Arſifettito.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arſifettito!</hi> What's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>A Rich perfume the Chymiſts make, and good againſt</l>
                  <l>Fits o'th' Mother. But what ſhall I do now? I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be turn'd away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I'le warrant thee, I'le place thee with <hi>Eugenia,</hi> ſhe</l>
                  <l>Shall take care of thee for mine and a Friends ſake</l>
                  <l>Of hers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, ay, that's <hi>Franciſco;</hi> but you have promis'd me</l>
                  <l>Often to tell me a ſecret concerns them; prethee</l>
                  <l>Do't now, Nurſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>But will you ne're ſpeak on't? If you do, I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Get no more money for thee, <hi>Jaſper;</hi> that's the way,</l>
                  <l>I get all, Chuck; no, no, no matter what's between them,</l>
                  <l>Truſt thou to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, Nurſe, I thought you had Lov'd me, but I ſee</l>
                  <l>You do not; you know I can keep ſecrets.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, but this is ſuch a one I dare not tell it; beſides;</l>
                  <l>It was not <hi>Eugenias</hi>-fault at firſt — alas, poor</l>
                  <l>Fool, ſhe was in a ſad taking, when ſhe found</l>
                  <l>Her Couzen <hi>Franciſco</hi> in Bed with her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>In Bed, ſayſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101837:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Lord bleſs me! what have I done? If you ſhould</l>
                  <l>Tell now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Ne're fear it, tell me all: I would not for the</l>
                  <l>World have miſt this Story, it makes a full amends</l>
                  <l>For all my Croſſes; come, Nurſe, prethee quickly</l>
                  <l>Tell me all paſſages.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I tell no more, my mind miſgives me I've ſaid</l>
                  <l>Too much already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Not tell me more, Old Beldame? Speak it quickly,</l>
                  <l>Or what I know ſhall ſoon unto my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>How now! Is this diſſembling too?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>No, 'tis as great a truth as what you told me of,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Franciſco</hi>'s Bedding with <hi>Eugenia;</hi> tell me the</l>
                  <l>Reſt, and by it ſave your Life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Dear <hi>Jaſper,</hi> be not angry, and I will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, Nurſe, do it, and then we'l kiſs and be Friends.</l>
                  <l>I ſhall have uſe of her.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Now thou ſhalt have my heart; and thus it is:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Franciſco</hi> doth often meet <hi>Eugenia</hi> i'th'</l>
                  <l>Garden, who, to avoid ſuſpition, after her Siſters</l>
                  <l>In Bed, by my means gets her Night-Gown, and</l>
                  <l>Puts it on ſo to avoid being known, ſhou'd any ſee her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, Excellent! when do they meet again?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I've promis'd him this Night, though ſhe was loath,</l>
                  <l>Till I told her he would but take his leave, for ſhe's</l>
                  <l>Grown a little backward, now ſhe's to marry <hi>Don Gerardo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Is ſhe to marry him, ſayſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I, ſure, for he makes Love to her, and ſhe's ſo hot</l>
                  <l>Upon't, that ſhe vows after this Night never to meet</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco</hi> any more; but I'le go Live with her,</l>
                  <l>And ſo ſhalt thou.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> will — i'th' Garden, ſayſt thou, and in her</l>
                  <l>Siſters Gown, no body with them!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, the Lord <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> he knows all, and alwayes</l>
                  <l>VVaits upon 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>That's well, keep thou the ſecret cloſe, and ne're fear me;</l>
                  <l>But if my Lord ſhould ask ſuſpitiouſly queſtions</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101837:8"/>
                  <l>About his Wife — name <hi>Pedro</hi> to him, ſay, when he's</l>
                  <l>From Home, that Fellow ſtayes too long within her</l>
                  <l>Chamber, and ſay, that <hi>Flora</hi> waits; leave me to prove</l>
                  <l>It true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, 'tis not ſo, I dare not tell my Lord ſo damn'd a Lye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Why? Y'are a Fool, there ſhall no hurt come of it,</l>
                  <l>Only we'l be Reveng'd of <hi>Pedro,</hi> and that Slut, for</l>
                  <l>They're our Enemies; beſides, if you won't, I'le ſwear</l>
                  <l>You told me ſo, and moreover, let him know all the</l>
                  <l>Reſt y'have told me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, don't be angry, and I'le do any thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Caelia, Pedro, <hi>and</hi> Flora.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, thou Old doting Fool! what, ſtill remain here!</l>
                  <l>What puniſhment is proper for thy Age? As for you,</l>
                  <l>Sirrah, I believe my Lord will find a way quickly to</l>
                  <l>Send you packing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>It may be ſo, but 'tis without a cauſe,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Impudent Villain! how I do hate thy ſight.</l>
                  <l>Follow you me.</l>
                  <stage>To Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> Cael. Nurſe, <hi>&amp;</hi> Flora.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>What, i'th' dumps, Seignior! all a mort for your</l>
                  <l>Miſtreſs, faith man, take it not ſo to heart, there are others</l>
                  <l>I'th World as Young, though few may be as handſome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, Sir, 'tis to be ſuppos'd; you can boaſt it by Experience,</l>
                  <l>There are Young Ladies for ſpruce <hi>'Pedro's — Jaſper</hi> —</l>
                  <l>Muſt be content with their Nurſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Content, ſay you? I, Marry, if ſhe content you not, the</l>
                  <l>Devil can't; why, ſhe's a Diſh of variety, like a huge</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Olio;</hi> there's all Ages of Women in her. Thou art</l>
                  <l>The happieſt man in a Miſtreſs, <hi>Jaſper</hi> — faith, I envy thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis very well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <p>Not too well neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>You may laugh; you ſtand on the top of Favour,</l>
                  <l>Have a care of falling down, I may catch you</l>
                  <l>One day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>No, never with an Old Woman; it's worſe then</l>
                  <l>Committing Inceſt; to Cuckold, for ought I know, a</l>
                  <l>dozen Generations.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101837:9"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Reſt you merry, I can leave you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <p>But I'le not quit you ſo.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio <hi>and</hi> Gerardo
<hi>Diſcourſing.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>In this, dear Friend, conſiſts my happineſs;</l>
                  <l>Therefore deny me not — Why pauſe you, Sir?</l>
                  <l>My fears are come about —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>What, hath <hi>Eugenia</hi> given her conſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſay not ſo, my Lord, but her denyals</l>
                  <l>VVere ſpoke ſo faintly, I Interpret well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Dear Friend, I am afraid you do miſtake</l>
                  <l>The Object of your Joyes, let me perſwade</l>
                  <l>You to believe, there's not that happineſs</l>
                  <l>In Marriage-Beds, as ſingle People gueſs,</l>
                  <l>No, no, ſo far from that, that thouſands be</l>
                  <l>Flatter'd by hopes to endleſs miſery.</l>
                  <l>And where there's two obtain their hearts deſire,</l>
                  <l>Ten thouſand miſs it, and in grief expire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>VVere theſe Poſitions true, there's no man, ſure,</l>
                  <l>If VViddowed once, could other VVives endure.</l>
                  <l>And yet we ſee the firſt depriv'd of Life,</l>
                  <l>There's few that ſeek not for a ſecond Wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true, though ſtrange, but yet our minds are ſuch,</l>
                  <l>As alwayes find too little, or too much;</l>
                  <l>Deſire's a Monſter, whoſe extended Maw</l>
                  <l>Is never fill'd, tho' it doth all things draw:</l>
                  <l>For we with envious Eyes do others ſee,</l>
                  <l>Who want our ills, and think they happy be,</l>
                  <l>Till we poſſeſſing what we wiſh'd before,</l>
                  <l>Find our ills doubl'd, and ſo wiſh for more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Suppoſe all true which you wou'd have me fear,</l>
                  <l>Ills in poſſeſſion ſtill the greateſt are:</l>
                  <l>And my deſires to ſuch a height do riſe,</l>
                  <l>T' attain their ends, I ſhou'd all elſe deſpiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Since y'are reſolv'd, I'le not your ends deny,</l>
                  <l>But pray my words prove falſe when e're you try;</l>
                  <l>Though well they ſpeak, who ſay the damned State,</l>
                  <l>Chiefly conſiſts in wiſhing things too late:</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101837:9"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eugenia's</hi> Father left her to my care,</l>
                  <l>Which truſt to end ſo well I did deſpair:</l>
                  <l>Then name the day of Marriage —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>No delay</l>
                  <l>My thoughts admit; I wiſh it were to day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>That cannot be, to Morrow I approve.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Time will flye ſlow, though Impt with wings of Love.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Caelia <hi>and</hi> Eugenia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I beg your pardon for a ſhort interruption.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, 'tis I have cauſe to beg your pardon,</l>
                  <l>Thus to detain your Lord, on's Wedding-day,</l>
                  <l>A Day in Juſtice ſhould be wholly yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord is happy ſo to be detain'd,</l>
                  <l>And I am alwayes happy when he's ſo.</l>
                  <l>But good, my Lord, your Ear —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, if you repent not what y'have ſaid,</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Whiſpers</hi> Anto. <hi>he takes a paper pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately out of her pocket.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>In anſwer to thoſe Vows of my Affection,</l>
                  <l>I then dare hope I may in time be happy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>Tho' I ne're thought your words were further means,</l>
                  <l>Then to paſs time away in Raillery;</l>
                  <l>Yet were my Anſwers ſuch, as if you had</l>
                  <l>Told me a real Story of your Love:</l>
                  <l>And the ſame Anſwers I'le again renew;</l>
                  <l>My Will's confin'd; my Father's laſt Commands</l>
                  <l>Left me no Choice but anothers will;</l>
                  <l>If I were free, I then durſt ſpeak my thoughts:</l>
                  <l>But I, in all, my Brother muſt obey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>He checks your Actions only, thoughts are free,</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe him willing, would you favour me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>But to ſuppoſe without his Will's a Crime,</l>
                  <l>If I that ſuppoſition ſhould declare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>I do confeſs I ſhould be loath to own</l>
                  <l>That Bleſſing which I rate above my Life,</l>
                  <l>If 'twere beſtow'd by any hands but yours;</l>
                  <l>Therefore by all your hopes I do conjure you,</l>
                  <l>If you diſlike my Love, Command my ſilence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>Interpret well my bluſhes, when I ſay</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101837:10"/>
                  <l>I cannot find a thought for ſuch Commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I am happy 'bove the reach of Envy;</l>
                  <l>For I have his conſent already granted,</l>
                  <l>He nam'd the day of Marriage as you enter'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſee, my Lord, that I had cauſe for fear,</l>
                  <l>Since I'm beſtow'd, and my conſent ne're askt.</l>
                  <l>Sure my dead Father ne're deſign'd it ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I beg your pardon, for a truth</l>
                  <l>Might well excuſe your Brother in this matter;</l>
                  <l>I urg'd to him I doubted not your favour,</l>
                  <l>On which Condition he did grant me his.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall hear further of it from himſelf,</l>
                  <l>Till when, I beg your pardon.</l>
                  <stage>Offers to go out.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Siſter, pray ſtay, for I have bus'neſs with you.</l>
                  <l>I know, my Dear, you never Lov'd that Fellow,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſince you do not, though he ſerves me well,</l>
                  <l>Yet I'm reſolv'd for this to part with him,</l>
                  <l>Tho' I could think a Penſion for your Nurſe,</l>
                  <l>To keep her at a diſtance, were as well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Though now her dotage makes her want diſcretion,</l>
                  <l>Her Love to us was great.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, trouble not your ſelf about it, he ſhall go.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I'le trouble you no further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>I'le wait upon you, Madam.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Gerar. <hi>and</hi> Cael.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Siſter, you know your Father was my Friend,</l>
                  <l>And was ſo confident that I was his,</l>
                  <l>He truſted all your Fortunes in my hands,</l>
                  <l>Though he had Brothers Living when he Dy'd,</l>
                  <l>He told you too, and left it in his VVill,</l>
                  <l>That what you had was mine, if you did Marry</l>
                  <l>VVithout my Approbation: Is't not true?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, 'tis a truth I'm glad of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe things your Kindred though, did call contrivance,</l>
                  <l>VVhich made their hatred riſe ſo much againſt me,</l>
                  <l>It makes a few'd betwixt our Families,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſoon would come to Blood, but for Reſpect</l>
                  <l>They bear my VVife, their Cozen.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101837:10"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>Brother, I cannot anſwer for their Actions,</l>
                  <l>My own Reſpects to you were never wanting.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not deny it, Siſter; and to prove</l>
                  <l>I never did, nor will deſerve worſe from you,</l>
                  <l>If you are willing now to change your State,</l>
                  <l>And know a man preferr'd in your Election,</l>
                  <l>Let him have Blood and worth, you and your Fortune</l>
                  <l>I freely will reſign into his hands.</l>
                  <l>Then truly ſpeak your thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>Surely, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>You'd ſcarcely think I ſhould be worth your care,</l>
                  <l>If I ſhould chooſe before you nam'd one to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Siſter, I ſee your Kindreds Jealouſies</l>
                  <l>Partly infects you too; but to remove them,</l>
                  <l>VVhat think you of <hi>Gerardo,</hi> for a Husband?</l>
                  <l>My wiſhes meet with yours, if he's their Object;</l>
                  <l>You know I'm no Diſſembler.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor ſhall you find me ſo; for I confeſs</l>
                  <l>In this you prove your Kindneſs, Care, and Juſtice;</l>
                  <l>And I muſt meet it with my greateſt thanks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm joyful for it; to morrow is the day,</l>
                  <l>A private Wedding will prevent all Rumour,</l>
                  <l>You'd beſt withdraw then to provide your ſelf.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Eugen.</stage>
                  <l>What Paper's this I got out of her Pocket?</l>
                  <l>Pray Heaven it be the right; it is the ſame,</l>
                  <l>The very ſame — what makes me tremble!</l>
                  <l>Is't horror or deſire, or both aſſault me?</l>
                  <l>Be it what it will, 'tis Hell to live in doubt;</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, my Conſcience ſayes 'tis Sacriledge —</l>
                  <l>What's that? A word by cunning Prieſts invented</l>
                  <l>To keep the Cheats they live by from our knowledge;</l>
                  <l>As the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> did with
<hi>Hieroglyfficks;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But be it what it will, a Name, or thing,</l>
                  <l>I'le read it, for't may Cure my Jealouſie,</l>
                  <l>And ſurely that exceeds Hells miſery.</l>
                  <l>But to my Cloſet, where no Eye can ſee,</l>
                  <l>All are call'd Pious, who live ſcandal free.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101837:11"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Eugenia <hi>and Nurſe.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>Since he has promis'd but to take his leave,</l>
                  <l>And neither then, nor never urge more Sin,</l>
                  <l>I am content to give him this laſt meeting.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>He'l be a glad man, I'm ſure — but what ſhall poor</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſper</hi> do?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>If he will marry you, I'le keep you both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Thank you, Madam, I'le tell him your good will.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat by this curſed Sin am I reduc'd to?</l>
                  <l>To be a Slave to Slaves; nay, worſe, a Bawd,</l>
                  <l>A Name ſo baſe, profeſt ones do deteſt it,</l>
                  <l>And yet I'm one, this curſed Helliſh Hagg has made me ſo.</l>
                  <l>The firſt did ſell, and then betray'd my Honour,</l>
                  <l>Yet thinks ſhe has oblig'd me by the Action.</l>
                  <l>Nay, I am forc't to ſay ſo now to pleaſe her;</l>
                  <l>Some heavenly Angel make me Chaſte again,</l>
                  <l>Or make me nothing, I am reſolv'd to try,</l>
                  <l>Before I'de ſtill live VVhore, I'de chooſe to dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm come to thank your Lady-ſhip for the great care,</l>
                  <l>Nurſe ſayes, you have of me; but faith, Madam, I</l>
                  <l>VVas ne're made to be Steel to a Tinder-Box; ſhe's</l>
                  <l>Meer Touch-wood; no, I'm not for Marrying great</l>
                  <l>Grannums: But if your Lady-ſhip knows any Young</l>
                  <l>Dame, that wants a ſtrong back to do her drudgery,</l>
                  <l>Though it be in her Lord's abſence, I'm content.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat, is the Fellow mad?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>No, Madam, not mad at all, but can as ſoberly keep</l>
                  <l>Councel as the beſt Young Gallant of 'em all; and am</l>
                  <l>As able to do the feat: Pleaſe your Lady-ſhip to try me,</l>
                  <l>And praiſe me as you find; if you diſlike my work,</l>
                  <l>I'le loſe my labour, and have nothing for my pains.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, ſtrange, unheard-of Impudence! Out, Villain.</p>
                  <stage>Ex.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>So ſcornful! Villain! Nay, if you call me ſo, 'tis time</l>
                  <l>To be ſo; what a Devil ayls my face, that ſhe contemns</l>
                  <l>Me thus? May be my Noſe is not long enough ſhe thinks,</l>
                  <l>Pox on her Pride, 'tis that or'e-comes her Leachery — I muſt</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101837:11"/>
                  <l>Alter my Trade, for I was ne're born I ſee to thrive by</l>
                  <l>Love; then I'le ſet up a ſhop of hatred, and the Wares I</l>
                  <l>Vent ſhall be Revenge, that may hit; but hold, my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>What have I got? Am I more ſatisfy'd</l>
                  <l>By this ſame Paper then I was before?</l>
                  <l>No, not at all; and yet why ſhould I not?</l>
                  <l>There's not a thought ſet down concerneth me —</l>
                  <l>Yet that's her policy —</l>
                  <l>She either fear'd that I ſhould get the Paper,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe on purpoſe did contrive I might;</l>
                  <l>But how can I know that? This Jealouſie,</l>
                  <l>If it continue long, will make me mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, the Devil has put him on this pin meerly</l>
                  <l>To do me a kindneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>And yet it muſt continue, who can Cure it?</l>
                  <l>Ay, there's it, who can Cure it? Then I muſt be mad!</l>
                  <l>Nay, I'm mad already, ſtark mad!—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>My good Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>What's the matter? I fear he heard me.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I come to take leave of your Lordſhip, I have</l>
                  <l>Enemies I hear have turn'd me going.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Is't not deſervedly, thou Goat?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes, it may be ſo, ſince they will have it ſo;</l>
                  <l>But if I had never ſeen, I had ne're been turn'd</l>
                  <l>A way for doing: If I were as ready to make</l>
                  <l>Miſchief, as I am fear'd to be; Nurſe and I had not</l>
                  <l>Been only the Sufferers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Explain your Riddle, Sirrah.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, let my Tongue come out e're I ſay any thing to</l>
                  <l>Diſquiet your Lordſhip, I love you better.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Diſquiet me! What lyes within thy power to ſay that</l>
                  <l>Can diſquiet me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nothing it may be, my Lady is my Lady, and</l>
                  <l>You are a kind Lord, that's all I know; ſo begging</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhips Diſcharge, I'm gone, and then your</l>
                  <l>Fears are over.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101837:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Villain, thou'ſt given me poyſon; my veins ſwell</l>
                  <l>With it, produce the Antidote, or I'le diſſect thy Soul</l>
                  <l>To find it out; what is't you know that can diſquiet me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I know little, my Lord, to'th' purpoſe, beſides, it will</l>
                  <l>But vex you, ſince there may be no harm in it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come, no going back, tell quickly what you know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I know, why, I know that my Lady hates me,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I told your Lordſhip the time ſhe was to</l>
                  <l>Deliver the Jewels and Money to <hi>Don Lewis,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>Still ſhe calls me falſe in being true to you — but —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>But what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>But if I ſhould ſay all I know — well, but let</l>
                  <l>That alone, good, my Lord, your Diſcharge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Vile Dog, doſt raiſe my Anger for to play with it?</l>
                  <l>I'le vent it upon thee then.</l>
                  <stage>Draws, and cuts at him.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, hold, my Lord, and I'le tell all I know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Let's hear it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>When you lay hid about <hi>Don Lewis</hi>'s death, I've</l>
                  <l>Often ſeen a Lady in the Night to meet two Men</l>
                  <l>I'th' Garden, but am not ſure it was your Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>What makes you name her then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Her Gown, I think it was her Gown.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Wa'ſt often, ſay you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, every Night, except you lay at home, for I</l>
                  <l>Took pains to watch, they never fail'd coming,</l>
                  <l>But there was but one of them went into the Houſe,</l>
                  <l>Sir, and he neither would not ſtay above an hour</l>
                  <l>At moſt: this is all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>All, quoth a! What Devil would have more,</l>
                  <l>If 'twas my Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I can't ſay that, but yet I dare be ſworn it was</l>
                  <l>Her Gown, I do believe, I mean, I think it was.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Could you not gueſs the men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>I think they were <hi>Franciſco</hi> and
<hi>Sebaſtian.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>It muſt be they; a plague upon their Fewds;</l>
                  <l>They can Revenge themſelves upon my Wife:</l>
                  <l>Go, call the Nurſe, this ſhe muſt needs conſpire in;</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101837:12"/>
                  <l>But keep all private from her.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Jaſper:</stage>
                  <l>Is ſhe ſo buckſome? Has ſhe more Kinſmen Stallions?</l>
                  <l>I'le cleanſe her Blood, or empty all her veins;</l>
                  <l>Confeſſions calls ſhe theſe! Betwixt Religion and her Leachery</l>
                  <l>The Devil dances Barley-break — but hold — why</l>
                  <l>May'nt the Rogue contrive this for Revenge?</l>
                  <l>For if I reflect his pretending not to tell, did but</l>
                  <l>Uſher in the Story. I muſt be cautious of a too light belief.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Caelia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, by Accident I've loſt a Paper, which troubles me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>A Paper, ſay you? I took up one i'th' Garden, and I</l>
                  <l>Think this is it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>It is, my Lord, and I rejoyce no other Perſon found it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis the Confeſſion that I told you of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I might have read it then, and ne're askt you, had</l>
                  <l>I but known it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>If your Lordſhip pleaſes you may read it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, I will not, but prethee keep it better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, there are ſome Tenants, who deſire to expreſs</l>
                  <l>Their Loves by Rural Recreations —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Bid e'm ſtay, their ſporrs are more in ſeaſon after Dinner.</l>
                  <l>So willing now to have it read, and yet before ſo backward!</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Cael.</stage>
                  <l>Why, this confirms me ſhe is falſe, it was contriv'd</l>
                  <l>On purpoſe for my ſight. The Devil's not ſo cunning</l>
                  <l>As a Woman.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
                  <l>Oh, Beldame, are you come? Tell me, you Bawd,</l>
                  <l>Who Whores my Wife? For Whore I know ſhe is,</l>
                  <l>And you're her Bawd. Tell me, I ſay, the man,</l>
                  <l>The place, the Circumſtance, and very time,</l>
                  <l>Or I will quarter thee, and throw thy fleſh to'th' dogs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, my Lord, I know nothing but that when</l>
                  <l>You're from Home, <hi>Pedro</hi> goes to her Chamber, and</l>
                  <l>Stays there all Night, but what they do, I know</l>
                  <l>Not, for none but <hi>Flora's</hi> with them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro!</hi> Oh monſtrous, ſhe would devour a Legion!</l>
                  <l>Is't every Night, do you ſay?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101837:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, every Night; but I durſt never tell you!</l>
                  <l>Alas, ſhe ſuckt theſe Breaſts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Shew me this Night <hi>Pedro,</hi> in Bed with her,</l>
                  <l>Or I will cut thy Tongue out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis impoſſible when you are at home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I will contrive a Journey out of Town, but will at</l>
                  <l>Twelve return, then let me in; for if you fail</l>
                  <l>I'le cut your Throat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I'le do my beſt.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro!</hi> What ſordid Devil prompted her to that?</l>
                  <l>Why, I am known to all the World a Cuckold;</l>
                  <l>The very Boys i'th' ſtreet muſt point at me;</l>
                  <l>But hold, this new Intelligence ſtruck out the old,</l>
                  <l>And made me quite forget about <hi>Franciſco.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Jaſper!</hi> I'm confirm'd my Wife's a Devil,</l>
                  <l>And I will ſend her to the reſt e're Morning;</l>
                  <l>Go and contrive a Letter from <hi>Don John;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall intimate he's ſick, and wants my preſence,</l>
                  <l>Then I'le contrive the reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not too raſh, my Lord, might I adviſe</l>
                  <l>You ſhould be certain e're you Acted ought.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>How can I be more certain then this Night,</l>
                  <l>To be Eye-witneſs of her Luſt my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>As Nurſe has undertook I ſhall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, Sir, but things may fail, and they not meet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Name a more certain way then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, there lives a Woman in the Suburbs</l>
                  <l>Mighty in Science, who by Art can tell</l>
                  <l>All that ſhe pleaſes, I'de have you go to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Is ſhe of your acquaintance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>No, my Lord, ſhe ſcorns ſuch things as me,</l>
                  <l>She's for the great ones; though for Charity,</l>
                  <l>She ſometimes helps poor people to their goods,</l>
                  <l>I'me ſure ſhe'd ſerve your Lordſhip.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I fear ſhe'l never truſt us, leſt we ſhould betray</l>
                  <l>Her to the Inquiſition.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101837:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>No fear of that, ſhe cannot be betray'd,</l>
                  <l>She knows Mens bus'neſs er'e they come unto her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Well then, contrive my abſence, I'le go thither,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure to know whether ſhe cheats or no,</l>
                  <l>For if ſhe names <hi>Don Lewis</hi> 'mongſt the reſt,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall believe her. Well, about the Letter.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you there with your Beares; <hi>Don Lewis</hi> ſay you?</l>
                  <l>Marry now I find 'twas Jealouſie of his Wife;</l>
                  <l>And not the matter of Money made him kill him,</l>
                  <l>Whether he was guilty or no; I'le be ſure he ſhan't</l>
                  <l>Be forgot, for I'le before hand to my Aunt, and tell</l>
                  <l>Her all; I hope, ſhe is a Witch; the People ſay ſo, a</l>
                  <l>Mighty Artiſt I am ſure ſhe is, for ſhe has done</l>
                  <l>Strange things, and all men fear her, beſides I</l>
                  <l>Know ſhe loves me, and will ſtrive all ſhe can to</l>
                  <l>Do me good, and hap what will my Lord will</l>
                  <l>Think me honeſt; for Night will ſurely ſhew his</l>
                  <l>Siſter to him, dreſt in's Ladyes Gown, what though</l>
                  <l>He kill her, the miſtake will lye o'th' Night, and not</l>
                  <l>On me, thus I make good the Villain that ſhe call'd</l>
                  <l>Me, in my Revenge on her; and if Nurſe fails me</l>
                  <l>Not, I'le have my Lady, and <hi>Pedro;</hi> finely firkt. —</l>
                  <l>When this is done, my Lord rewards my care,</l>
                  <l>Let him the danger I'le the profit ſhare.</l>
                  <l>And ſince things Excellent commended be,</l>
                  <l>'Tſhall be my Aym t'excell in Villany.</l>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>The End of the firſt Act.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101837:14"/>
               <head>Act the Second.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jaſper <hi>and the Witch.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>'THis kindneſs, Aunt, I beg, your Art muſt do;</l>
                  <l>For I have no way elſe to ſave my place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, 'tis impoſſible; I've no ſuch Art</l>
                  <l>As People think, to call up Spirits to me;</l>
                  <l>Nor know I any thing, but what is told me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Now you diſſemble, Aunt, for han't you often</l>
                  <l>Rais'd Storms, have rent up Trees, and ſhook ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Towers? Seeming to threaten Nature with it's end;</l>
                  <l>And at ſuch times have ſent ſtrange ſhaped</l>
                  <l>Spirits, who have reſtored to owners ſtolen Goods.</l>
                  <l>Theſe things ſo many know, it is impoſſible</l>
                  <l>For you to keep it private; but I find,</l>
                  <l>Rather then truſt me with your mighty ſecrets,</l>
                  <l>Or help me with your Art, you'l ſee my Ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe things you ſpeak of, people think I do,</l>
                  <l>And ſo I'de have e'm; for 'tis the only way I have to Live:</l>
                  <l>The Vulgar People love to be deluded;</l>
                  <l>And things the moſt unlikely they moſt dote on;</l>
                  <l>A ſtrange Diſeaſe in Cattle, Hogs or Pigs,</l>
                  <l>Or any Accident in Cheeſe or Butter;</l>
                  <l>Though't be but Natural, or a Sluts fault,</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſtrait be Witchcraft! Oh, the Witch was here!</l>
                  <l>The Ears or Tail is burn'd, the Churn is burn'd;</l>
                  <l>And this to hurt the Witch, when all the while</l>
                  <l>They're likeſt Witches that believe ſuch Cures;</l>
                  <l>Could I do all that People think I can,</l>
                  <l>I'de ne're take pains to find out ſtolen Goods,</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101837:14"/>
                  <l>Or hold intelligence with Thieves to bring e'm,</l>
                  <l>Meerly to get my Bread; no, I would make</l>
                  <l>The Univerſe pay Tribute to my power,</l>
                  <l>And all the Bug-bear Lords Inquiſitors</l>
                  <l>More tremble at my Name then I do now</l>
                  <l>At theirs: Ah, <hi>Jaſper,</hi> would I raiſe</l>
                  <l>Storms when I would, blaſt Corn, turn Rivers backward,</l>
                  <l>Change ſhapes, mov'd where I pleas'd i'th' Air,</l>
                  <l>And that ſo faſt, as thought it ſelf would</l>
                  <l>Hardly overtake me:</l>
                  <l>What is't I could not do? if all were true</l>
                  <l>The Fooliſh People think, the Pope himſelf would</l>
                  <l>Quickly loſe Reſpect,</l>
                  <l>And none be thought infallible but I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm ſure I tremble for your want of power,</l>
                  <l>More then I ſhould to ſee Hells dreadfull'ſt ſhape,</l>
                  <l>For I muſt flye the Town.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſper,</hi> not ſo; though I can raiſe no Devils,</l>
                  <l>Yet I Confederate with Rogues and Taylors,</l>
                  <l>Things that can ſhape themſelves like Elves,</l>
                  <l>And Goblins —</l>
                  <l>And often do like Spirits haunt great Houſes,</l>
                  <l>Moſt times to ſteal, but many times for mirth;</l>
                  <l>Theſe I'le ſoon ſend for; ariſe, my
<hi>Pincula.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter a little Devil, and tumbles the Summerſet.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Heav'ns bleſs me! ſave me, good Aunt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>From what? You Fool, 'tis but a little Boy,</l>
                  <l>Which I inſtruct to carry on my Cheats:</l>
                  <l>Come, leave your Fooling, I have bus'neſs for you;</l>
                  <l>Uncaſe your ſelf, and quickly go and find</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ranter,</hi> and <hi>Swaſh, Dive, Fob, Snap, Gilt,</hi> and <hi>Pick-lock,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe are my Archeſt Devils; as you go</l>
                  <l>Call upon <hi>Dog'rell</hi> the Ballad-maker, and ſay</l>
                  <l>I want him ſtrait, bid them be ſure</l>
                  <l>To bring home half a dozen more with them,</l>
                  <l>For I ſhall need their help, let e'm not fail,</l>
                  <l>For money's to be got.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devil.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis that will make e'm come; I'le haſte, forſooth.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:101837:15"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm glad it's gone, for ſurely it was a Devil,</l>
                  <l>What ever you pretend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou'rt a Fool:</l>
                  <l>It was a Boy, I tell thee, and no Devil;</l>
                  <l>Nor am I a ſorcereſs, though I could wiſh</l>
                  <l>To do thee good I was: But 'tis no matter;</l>
                  <l>Bring thou thy Lord, I'le practice well enough</l>
                  <l>To make him think all true, that I ſhall ſhew him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>You now Revive my Drooping Spirits, Aunt, and</l>
                  <l>Make my hopes grow ſtrong! Ah ſweet Revenge,</l>
                  <l>How my ſoul Dances but with thoughts of it;</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſt me, Aunt, to get this mighty Bleſſing, and I</l>
                  <l>Shall dye your ſlave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>O rare Boy!</l>
                  <l>How I rejoyce to ſee this Spirit in thee,</l>
                  <l>For 'tis the vertue of our Family</l>
                  <l>To ſeek Revenge, not baſely ſwallow wrongs:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Sancho De Monſalvo,</hi> thy Grandſire</l>
                  <l>Was for a while Vice-Admiral of Spain,</l>
                  <l>But then diſgrac'd turn'd Pyrate and Reveng'd</l>
                  <l>With Fire and Sword on all Mankind, the wrongs</l>
                  <l>He thought the Court had baſely plac'd on him;</l>
                  <l>At laſt he was betray'd and loſt his head,</l>
                  <l>Thy Father turn'd Bandetto, what he got</l>
                  <l>I did diſpoſe of for him; but his Fate</l>
                  <l>Betray'd him too to Death by Execution:</l>
                  <l>Since when I by theſe Arts do ſtrive to live,</l>
                  <l>And thou art forc'd to ſerve —</l>
                  <l>That very Lord, who does thoſe Lands</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſs ſhould have been thine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>But will e're long mount to ſome higher ſphere,</l>
                  <l>Or dye in the attempt; this Plot, perhaps, may do,</l>
                  <l>And I thereby obtain ſome part of my Eſtate</l>
                  <l>Again; for if the plotted miſchiefs ſhall ſucceed,</l>
                  <l>I'le tell him whom I am, and my reſolves, either</l>
                  <l>To ſhare his Fortunes or Reveal all. Then I will</l>
                  <l>Riſe <hi>Don Jaſper De Monſalvo,</hi> and Cheek by Jole,</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:101837:15"/>
                  <l>Ask how <hi>Antonio</hi> does. Then don't forget the names.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <p>Not one of them: I know them very well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Farewell, Dear Aunt, but don't you ſeem to know me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Out you great Fool! What become my Inſtructer?</l>
                  <l>Be careful of your ſelf, and fear not me. Farewel, boy.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio, Gerardo, Caelia, Eugenia, <hi>as to a Maſque, and take their ſeats.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you heard, Madam, what they repreſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caelia.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I'm told they mean to play the Gipſies,</l>
                  <l>And tell our fortunes to us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>I would they could.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>If all Man's life determin'd is before,</l>
                  <l>I would not know my Deſtiny me-thinks,</l>
                  <l>For good is beſt, when leaſt it is Expected;</l>
                  <l>And bad fore-ſeen is doubl'd by our fear</l>
                  <l>Things certain no fore-knowledge can prevent</l>
                  <l>Such knowledge only can bring diſcontent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>In this with you I perfectly agree.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet for all that I wiſh I could foreſee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caelia.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, what profit by it wou'd you gain?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twould cure doubt to me the deadlieſt pain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Doubt is th'effect of fear or Jealouſie,</l>
                  <l>Two Paſſions which to Reaſon give the Lye</l>
                  <l>For fear torments, but never does aſſiſt,</l>
                  <l>And Jealouſie is love loſt in a Miſt.</l>
                  <l>Both Hood-wink truth, then go to blind-mans buff,</l>
                  <l>Cry here, then there, ſeem to direct enought:</l>
                  <l>But all the while ſhift place making the mind</l>
                  <l>As it goes out of breath deſpair to find.</l>
                  <l>And if at laſt ſomething it ſtumbles on,</l>
                  <l>Perhaps it calls it falſe and then 'tis gone.</l>
                  <l>If true, what's gain'd only juſt time to ſee</l>
                  <l>A breachleſs Play a Game at Liberty;</l>
                  <l>That has no other end then this, that men</l>
                  <l>Run to be tyr'd juſt to ſet down agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a truth, and ſo for ought I know,</l>
                  <l>To the ſame purpoſe tends all things we do:</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:101837:16"/>
                  <l>Life's a Diſeaſe, and yet we ſeldom ſay,</l>
                  <l>That Man is ſick whom we ſee laugh and play;</l>
                  <l>And 'tis as well to bid the Bed-rid ride,</l>
                  <l>As to bid Men in doubt be ſatisfy'd:</l>
                  <l>For 'tis the mind's Diſeaſe, and Phyſick ſhould</l>
                  <l>Be proper to't, or elſe the Patient's fool'd.</l>
                  <l>And there's no Drug in Nature doubt to Cure</l>
                  <l>But only one, and that is to be ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Circumſtance, my Lord, if well apply'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I've known that often fail, when it was try'd.</l>
                  <l>But they come —</l>
                  <stage>Flouriſh.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter firſt Gipſie, and ſings.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gipſie.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>COme, come, away; follow, follow your Prince,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I am King of the ſwarthy Complexions;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Follow me that can lead you through Chimneys and Chinks</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſteal Bacon and Peaſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nay, ſometimes with eaſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To a Feaſt of the choyceſt Confections.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come, follow me then, come away, come away.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter ſecond Gipſie, and ſings.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Gip.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We know no Rebellion, but obey, but obey,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To our King we are juſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And true to our truſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leaving diſcord to thoſe, that their Princes oppoſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When by the Spirit of Treaſon in Non-ſence they pray.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter all the reſt, and ſing.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We know,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come then, and follow, a prize, a prize, a prize.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Give the word then, and holloa.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A prize, a prize, a prize.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101837:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here are Gallants and Ladies have Fortunes to tell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We'l tell e'm good Fortune if they give us aſpell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A hand croſt with ſilver the Spirit infuſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There's no Prophet lately that mettle refuſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Men get Heaven now by Bargain and Sale.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maſſes, Trentals, and Dirges</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Are not had for no Charges,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And a Vicar for nothing won't tell you a Tale.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maſſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All things are bought and ſold.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Fortune goes with Gold.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fall on to your Trading then.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Men Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>W'are for the Ladies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom. Gip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And we for the Men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Gip.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>To <hi>Cael.</hi> Lady, you have loſt a Lover,</l>
                  <l>Croſs my hand, I'le more diſcover.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Gip.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>To <hi>Anto.</hi> My Lord, I know you baſeneſs ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>And would be loath to wear a Horn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Gip.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>To <hi>Eug.</hi> Lady, ſome do ſpeak you fair,</l>
                  <l>That hatred to your welfare bear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Gip.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>To <hi>Ger.</hi> My Lord, you Love a handſom Lady,</l>
                  <l>She Loves you as well it may be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip. ſings.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus we ſeldom miſs the matter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Things paſt we can tell, by theſe Generals well,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ne're ſtay to prove the truth of the latter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Things paſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. To <hi>Cael.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall Live long and happily, Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. To <hi>Anto.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I can tell you, good Fortunes your Friend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. To <hi>Eug.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall e're long play with your own Baby.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. To <hi>Ger.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Your Love, my Lord, will have good end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Gip. ſings.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus we Live merrily, merrily, merrily,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And thus to our Dancing we ſing;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our Lands and our Livings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lye in others believings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When to all Men we tell the ſame thing:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And thus to our Dancing we ſing.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus we,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <stage>An Antique of Gipſies, and Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101837:17"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>By this we ſee that all the Worlds a Cheat,</l>
                  <l>Where truths and falſhoods lye ſo intermixt,</l>
                  <l>And are ſo like each other, that 'tis hard</l>
                  <l>To find the difference; who would not think theſe People</l>
                  <l>A real pack of ſuch as we call Gipſies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Things perfectly alike are but the ſame;</l>
                  <l>And theſe were Gipſies, if we did not know</l>
                  <l>How to conſider them the contrary:</l>
                  <l>So in Terreſtial things there is not one</l>
                  <l>But takes its Form and Nature from our fancy;</l>
                  <l>Not its own being, and is what we do think it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>But truth is ſtill it ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>No, not at all, as truth appears to us;</l>
                  <l>For oftentimes</l>
                  <l>That is a truth to me that's falſe to you,</l>
                  <l>So 'twould not be if it was truly true.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Pedro <hi>and a Servant, with a Letter to</hi> Antonio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, <hi>Don John</hi> ſalutes you in that Letter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>How does my Couzen, Friend?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam, I fear he's drawing near his end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>'Pray Heav'n divert it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>The Letter ſhews, that Death did guide his hand;</l>
                  <l>It only ſays, Oh Friend, come now or never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>How did his Sickneſs take him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Chacing the Buck too hard; he hot with Labour,</l>
                  <l>Drunk of a cooling Spring too eagerly,</l>
                  <l>And that has given him pains, the Doctors ſay,</l>
                  <l>Will give him Death immediately.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>Heav'n grant him help.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Return, and tell thy Lord, I'm at thy heels.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro,</hi> bring my Boots, and bid two Horſes be made</l>
                  <l>Ready.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>Whom do you take, my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro:</hi> — but hold, <hi>Jaſper</hi> is not diſcharg'd,</l>
                  <l>I'le ee'n take him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jaſper,</hi> my Lord! Pray take not him.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Ped. <hi>with Boots.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Why not him, there are no Nurſes there?</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:101837:17"/>
                  <l>Where's <hi>Jaſper Pedro?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſaid he wou'd not dine, and went</l>
                  <l>Abroad, yet I ſuppoſe he may be now in's Chamber.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Reach my Bootes, who has worn 'em lately?</l>
                  <l>I do believe you get into my Bootes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <p>I, my Lord.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Strikes</hi> Pedro <hi>with a Boot top.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>I, you, my Rogue! Go, ſee for <hi>Jaſper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Pedro.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord! Why do you thus diſturb your ſelf?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſee the blow don't maim him, you need</l>
                  <l>Not be concern'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Caelia.</speaker>
                  <p>What means my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>As you hate <hi>Jaſper,</hi> I hate whom I pleaſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>His ſight ſtrikes terror to me!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jaſper,</hi> make ready, you muſt go with me.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Jaſp.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Here on my knees I beg you would not take him:</l>
                  <l>But if you be reſolv'd, let me go too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>That cannot be: Don <hi>John's</hi> a Batchellor,</l>
                  <l>And is not fitted to have Women gueſts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>I will diſpence with any thing, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Then let me go, or do not take <hi>Jaſper.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, I muſt break this Childiſh way of yours,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſper</hi> ſhall go, and you ſhall ſtay at home,</l>
                  <l>And ſo Farewell; make merry with our Friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not reſolve, my Lord; ſee how ſhe takes it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>This paſſion ſoon will over; farewell, Friend,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall return to give <hi>Eugenia</hi> to you.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Anto.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>I ne're perceiv'd his will to reign before,</l>
                  <l>Some ſudden fancy makes him Obſtinate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>So, give her Air, ſhe comes to her ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is my Lord! What gone! am I deluded?</l>
                  <l>I Saw an Angel lead him back again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Her fancy is diſturb'd, make no anſwer:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Siſter, where's my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not diſturb your ſelf, my Brother's well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>Get me a horſe, for I will follow him.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101837:18"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio <hi>Bleeding.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Fetch me ſome water there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>My Dream was true, my Deareſt Lord's return'd!</l>
                  <l>What makes you Bleed?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>As I was lifting up my Foot to the Stirrop, my Noſe</l>
                  <l>Guſht out a Bleeding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eugen.</speaker>
                  <l>My Siſter dreamt, an Angel led you back,</l>
                  <l>And I believe it now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray take ſome other with you, I, if you pleaſe</l>
                  <l>Will keep you Company.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>No, I'm reſolv'd to ſtay, and ſend him word, I am</l>
                  <l>Took ill my ſelf; my Noſe leaves Bleeding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſatisfy'd, my Lord, you do not go, and therefore</l>
                  <l>Will Retire.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex. all but</hi> Anto. <hi>and</hi> Gerar.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Do ſo, my Dear.</l>
                  <l>Now I muſt tell my Friend, I dare not ſtay,</l>
                  <l>'Twould look but ill to ſay a Bleeding Noſe</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Don Antonio</hi> ſlight his dying Friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>If that was all, it would; but yet reflect</l>
                  <l>There are more Prodigies forbid this Journey</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Caeſar</hi> had t'avoyd the Senate-Houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Had <hi>Caeſar</hi> not been ſlain, thoſe Accidents</l>
                  <l>We now call Prodigies, had been forgot;</l>
                  <l>And ſo will theſe when I am ſafe return'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Conſider but your Ladies high concern,</l>
                  <l>Her ſuddain ſounding, and recovery,</l>
                  <l>On which ſhe cry'd an Angel brings him back,</l>
                  <l>Your Bleeding and Return ſpeaks ſhe dream't true,</l>
                  <l>The ſtopping of it too was not the leaſt,</l>
                  <l>All theſe together force me to believe</l>
                  <l>That you from heav'n theſe warnings did receive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Surely, <hi>Gerardo,</hi> we muſt heav'n offend</l>
                  <l>To think that it theſe Accidents ſhould ſend.</l>
                  <l>It is detraction to the Pow'rs above,</l>
                  <l>To think they ſuffer what they don't approve;</l>
                  <l>For if they did this to divert my ill,</l>
                  <l>They go about, for they might change my will:</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:101837:18"/>
                  <l>But mine's more firm; nay, more, ſhould I not go,</l>
                  <l>The threaten'd ill I meet, for ought I know;</l>
                  <l>For if their boads be certain, then I may</l>
                  <l>Meet th' effects whether I go or ſtay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Vainly we ſpeak of heav'n, when vainly we</l>
                  <l>By human Wit ſet Rules to heav'ns decree,</l>
                  <l>The pow'r that made us gave us ſcope of will,</l>
                  <l>Freely to take the good, or chooſe the ill:</l>
                  <l>And though it can, it does not change that courſe,</l>
                  <l>Only perſwades to Act what it could force.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>This you believe, but you muſt pardon me,</l>
                  <l>If in this point I don't with you agree;</l>
                  <l>For if to Man ſuch a free-will be given,</l>
                  <l>That damns all Praeſcience and ſo baffles heav'n:</l>
                  <l>But I delay whilſt Reaſon bids me go,</l>
                  <l>And Reaſon 'tis, ſince it to me is ſo,</l>
                  <l>Then pray divert my Wife, ſo farewell, Friend.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell: May all my to nothing tend;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill I fear what ſhould the Reaſon be,</l>
                  <l>That I ſhou'd fear, yet nothing fearful ſee,</l>
                  <l>I am reſolv'd to ſend ſome Servants out</l>
                  <l>Shall wait him at a diſtance;</l>
                  <l>In doing all I can, I do the beſt,</l>
                  <l>I can no more, let heav'n do the reſt.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Don Franciſco <hi>and Nurſe.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, 'tis ſo ſweet a ſin to Wench in danger,</l>
                  <l>That I am like to loſe the beſt part of my Recreation;</l>
                  <l>But prethee Nurſe, tell me, what cauſes this change?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Now if I would be hang'd, I cannot forbear telling.</l>
                  <l>Faith, my Lord, <hi>Gerardo</hi>'s like to be the Man now,</l>
                  <l>Though I am for your Lordſhip ſtill, you're my beſt Friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>By heav'n I'le be his Death, and hers to boot;</l>
                  <l>Can ſhe ſlight me for him, he Whore our Kindred!</l>
                  <l>When did he firſt enjoy her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo, my Lord, he's to Marry her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, if't be ſo; then I'm Reveng'd already,</l>
                  <l>For's joyning with <hi>Antonio</hi> 'gainſt our houſe,</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101837:19"/>
                  <l>He's Antidated Cuckold, and by me!</l>
                  <l>O rare Revenge! There's for thy News, Nurſe.</l>
                  <stage>Gives money to her.</stage>
                  <l>Were all my Enemies but ſerv'd the ſame;</l>
                  <l>At a more full Revenge I'de never aim.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Me-thinks you ſhould not be ſo merry for loſing my</l>
                  <l>Lady; 'faith, had I known it, you ſhould not have come</l>
                  <l>Into the place you wot'on, by my means.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, be not angry, Nurſe, I find her drift,</l>
                  <l>She loves our family, and ſtudies to Revenge it.</l>
                  <l>To make him Cuckold; how it pleaſes me!</l>
                  <l>Poyſon, nor Poniards is not half ſo well,</l>
                  <l>Go, tell her; Nurſe I'm glad ſhe takes this way:</l>
                  <l>I glory in her love! by Heaven I do,</l>
                  <l>I'le find Sebaſtian out, and laugh with him,</l>
                  <l>Till I e'en ſplit my ſides.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you'le tell no body I hope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>No, none but him:</l>
                  <l>To ſay as he goes by, there goes my Cuckold;</l>
                  <l>And then to laugh, go Nurſe, and tell her</l>
                  <l>I'le be ſure to meet —</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Another double Piſtoll for my <hi>Jaſper!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'le have him one whole night for this.</l>
                  <l>For to ſpeak truth, I find the Rogue does not love me:</l>
                  <l>Heavens! What a bad world is this,</l>
                  <l>An Old Woman, though never ſo willing,</l>
                  <l>Can ſcarce get a friend for ready money:</l>
                  <l>When ſuch as <hi>Eugenia</hi> can make the Gold fly about;</l>
                  <l>But time will come ſhe muſt be fain to turn tail,</l>
                  <l>And pay for one as I do, or go without.</l>
                  <l>But it pleaſes me, my Lady ſays, he ſhall be my husband,</l>
                  <l>Then I ſhall need give money no longer: for faith if he</l>
                  <l>Be negligent, I'le ring him a Peal to quicken him to his duty.</l>
                  <l>Thus marry'd once, I'le doe like other wives</l>
                  <l>That make their husbands drudge for quiet lives.</l>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>The End of the Second Act.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:101837:19"/>
               <head>Act the Third.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Don Gerardo <hi>with a Book in his Hand.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Song.</head>
                     <head type="sub">1.</head>
                     <l>SOme Happy Soul come down and tell</l>
                     <l>What Joys are thoſe with you do dwell?</l>
                     <l>If it be Happineſs like ours below,</l>
                     <l>Which from our want of ills does only flow,</l>
                     <l>Then 'tis plain that mighty theam</l>
                     <l>Of Immortality is but a Dream.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>'Tis Love, 'tis Love, for nothing can</l>
                     <l>Give real Happineſs to Man,</l>
                     <l>But Joys like thoſe that Lovers Souls enjoy,</l>
                     <l>Which here on Earth there's nothing can deſtroy;</l>
                     <l>Ay, ay, 'tis Love only can be</l>
                     <l>The Happy Souls endleſs felicity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>What a dull, heavy load hangs on my Soul!</l>
                  <l>Weighing me down to Earth, as if 'twould ſay</l>
                  <l>'Twas weary of its Burthen, and reſolv'd</l>
                  <l>To ſhake it off, and mix with its firſt matter;</l>
                  <l>What is the thing, call'd Death, we mortals ſhun?</l>
                  <l>Is't ſome real, or is't a fancy only?</l>
                  <l>Like that imaginary point in Mathematicks;</l>
                  <l>Not to be found only in definition:</l>
                  <l>It is no more: Death, like your Childrens Bug-bears,</l>
                  <l>Is fear'd by all, yet has no other Being</l>
                  <l>Then what weak fancy gives it; 'tis a Line,</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:101837:20"/>
                  <l>But yet imaginary, drawn betwixt</l>
                  <l>Time and that dreadful thing Eternity;</l>
                  <l>I, that's the thing, 'tis fear'd; for now I find it:</l>
                  <l>Eternity which puzzles all the World,</l>
                  <l>To name the Inhabitants that People it:</l>
                  <l>Eternity, whoſe undiſcover'd Countrey</l>
                  <l>We Fools divide, before we come to ſee it;</l>
                  <l>Making one part contain all happineſs,</l>
                  <l>The other miſery, then unſeen fight for't.</l>
                  <l>Loſing our certains for uncertainties;</l>
                  <l>All Sects pretending to a Right of choyce;</l>
                  <l>Yet none go willingly to take their part,</l>
                  <l>For they all doubt what they pretend to know,</l>
                  <l>And fear to mount, leſt they ſhould fall below:</l>
                  <l>Be't as it will; my Actions ſhall be juſt,</l>
                  <l>And for my future State I Heav'n will truſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a Servant.</stage>
               <l>Return'd already; what can be the cauſe?</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, <hi>Don Antonio</hi> likewiſe is return'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>What reaſon had he for it, doſt thou know?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I do not; for we by your appointment</l>
                  <l>Having took Horſe, did with our greateſt ſpeed</l>
                  <l>Purſue the Road ſhould lead us to <hi>Don John</hi>'s;</l>
                  <l>When near a Thicket ſtands ſome two Miles off,</l>
                  <l>I ſpy'd <hi>Antonio</hi> lying on the ground,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Jaſper</hi> walking of the Horſes by him,</l>
                  <l>Fearing his ſeeing us, we took the Thicket,</l>
                  <l>Where ſhelter'd from their Eyes, I left my Fellows.</l>
                  <l>But I approach'd as near as poſſible,</l>
                  <l>Hoping I did you Service, if I could</l>
                  <l>By their Diſcourſe gather their cauſe of ſtay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas like thy ſelf, both diligent and prudent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>But all my care did ſignifie but little,</l>
                  <l>The Wind blew freſh, and ruſtling in the Wood,</l>
                  <l>Wholly deſtroy'd their Voyces, ſo that few words</l>
                  <l>Of what they ſaid I heard; and thoſe I did,</l>
                  <l>Came ſo divided they had no connexion.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101837:20"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſort of Actions did you then perceive?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I ſaw <hi>Antonio</hi> much diſturb'd;</l>
                  <l>Sometimes he'd riſe and walk a turn or two</l>
                  <l>With eager pace, then ſtop as ſuddenly,</l>
                  <l>Then ſtamp and tear his hair; then loudly cry,</l>
                  <l>She's dead, ſhe's dead! Oh, <hi>Caelia,</hi> Oh,
<hi>Antonio!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then lye him down again, and reſt a ſpace:</l>
                  <l>Sometimes call <hi>Jaſper</hi> to him, talk a while,</l>
                  <l>And ſoon again riſe in another Paſſion;</l>
                  <l>Seldom I heard a word, except a Curſe!</l>
                  <l>Or now and then a Name; as <hi>Lewis, Caelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro, Franciſco, Flora;</hi> nay, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes I heard your Name, and then <hi>Engenia's;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then ſuddenly holding his hands to Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>He'd down again, and there a while would role.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe Actions ſure did ſeem a perfect madneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſeem'd indeed a madneſs methodiz'd,</l>
                  <l>Like theirs who are Tranſported far with Paſſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>But how perceiv'd you <hi>Jaſper</hi> bear himſelf?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Quite in another manner, but as ſtrange!</l>
                  <l>For when his Lord look'd down, his looks would be</l>
                  <l>As full of mirth, ready to burſt in Laughter;</l>
                  <l>That I perceiv'd he ſcarce contain'd himſelf:</l>
                  <l>But if his Lord did look about to ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>Then was his Face demure, with hand on Breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Turning his Eyes to Heav'n, and groaning ſighs,</l>
                  <l>As you have ſeen, my Lord, a Canting Preacher</l>
                  <l>Aiming to cheat his Audience, wanting matter,</l>
                  <l>Sigh to ſeem Holy, till he thought on ſomething.</l>
                  <l>So at that diſtance ſeem'd his Actions to me;</l>
                  <l>But when his back was turn'd, the Raſcal would</l>
                  <l>Make Mouths, and point with ſigns of greateſt ſcorn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>There is ſome Fatal Villany in this;</l>
                  <l>Some Myſtery beyond my Fathoming:</l>
                  <l>But how long ſtaid they thus?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>About two hours, when mounting both their Horſes,</l>
                  <l>I took mine, and un-eſpy'd did dogg e'm to the City,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:101837:21"/>
                  <l>And where they Hous'd I know not; for they enter'd</l>
                  <l>Remote from Home, and I i'th' ſtreets ſoon loſt e'm.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Do both your Fellows know this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>No, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>I did not think it would become my Duty</l>
                  <l>To tell them any thing but what they ſaw.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>I never knew thee yet miſtake thy truſt;</l>
                  <l>Thy ſecrecy was well: Preſerve it ſtill,</l>
                  <l>For I muſt uſe it further, therefore go,</l>
                  <l>And Charge your Piſtols, we muſt walk a Round</l>
                  <l>About <hi>Antonio</hi>'s Houſe to watch their motion;</l>
                  <l>For there the Scene muſt lye of this deſign;</l>
                  <l>If there be miſchief in't, thy courage now</l>
                  <l>(If theirs occaſion) muſt again be try'd.</l>
                  <l>And well Rewarded too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſo, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Above all other wayes in that you truſt it.</l>
                  <l>But I'le be gone, and Execute your Orders.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>A Faithful Servant is the beſt of Friends,</l>
                  <l>Since he is neareſt alwayes to aſſiſt us;</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, I cannot gueſs from all I've heard,</l>
                  <l>The cauſe that ſhould diſturb <hi>Antonio;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Except 'tis Jealouſie: Yet how can that be?</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Caelia's</hi> vitious there's no vertuous Women.</l>
                  <l>But now I think how much he rail'd at Marriage,</l>
                  <l>And more our Arguments concerning doubt,</l>
                  <l>Theſe things perſwade he's Jealous! But of whom?</l>
                  <l>The more I think, the more I am confounded!</l>
                  <l>How Clouded Man</l>
                  <l>Doubts firſt, and from one doubt doth ſoon proceed</l>
                  <l>A thouſand more in ſolving of the firſt;</l>
                  <l>Like Nighted Travellers we loſe our way;</l>
                  <l>Then every <hi>Ignis Fatuus</hi> makes us ſtray.</l>
                  <l>By the falſe Lights of Reaſon led about,</l>
                  <l>Till we arrive where we at firſt ſet out:</l>
                  <l>"Nor ſhall we e're Truths perfect High-way ſee,</l>
                  <l>"Till dawns the Day-break of Eternity.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:101837:21"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Eugenia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>I am amaz'd the Nurſe ſhould ſtay ſo long;</l>
                  <l>My Anger makes each minute ſeem an hour:</l>
                  <l>That Woman is a thing made up of miſchief;</l>
                  <l>Some Fatal Devil ſure did guide the Choyce</l>
                  <l>My Mother made, in chooſing her our Nurſe.</l>
                  <l>She's Fool to th' height: And yet hath wit enough</l>
                  <l>To tread all Labyrinths of Treachery;</l>
                  <l>But that's no wonder: For who's Treacherous</l>
                  <l>That wants not Eyes to ſee it's ugly Form?</l>
                  <l>For now I fear, and I believe not vainly,</l>
                  <l>That Villain, <hi>Jaſper,</hi> knows all my concerns,</l>
                  <l>Or what could prompt him to that Impudence</l>
                  <l>He did expreſs in his addreſs to day.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
                  <l>Thou fatal Hagg, thou Mother of all miſchief,</l>
                  <l>What Devil taught thy perjur'd Tongue the way</l>
                  <l>To tell the ſhame which thou didſt firſt occaſion?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray what ayls you, Madam, are you mad?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh I was, as I have cauſe enough,</l>
                  <l>For then I ſhould not know the ſhame attends me,</l>
                  <l>In being Table-talk for every Raſcal,</l>
                  <l>As thou (Hell thank thee for it) now haſt made me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I made you Table-talk! There's no ſuch thing;</l>
                  <l>I've been too faithful to you, that I have;</l>
                  <l>Loſing my ſleep full oft to watch your pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>And is this all I get? It is no matter, I</l>
                  <l>Shall be even with you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Threaten on (for thou haſt Acted all thy threats, Imp)</l>
                  <l>In letting <hi>Jaſper</hi> know my ſhame and folly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſper</hi> knows nothing, that he does not, from me,</l>
                  <l>And I will ask him; fore your face, I will,</l>
                  <l>If I e're ſaid <hi>Franciſco</hi> lay with you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis plain, thy guilt tranſported thee to madneſs,</l>
                  <l>Elſe thou wouldſt never make thy Tongue a Herauld</l>
                  <l>So loud, for to proclaim to all the Houſe</l>
                  <l>The Action you'd perſwade me ſtill is ſecret.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101837:22"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>If you talk lowd your ſelf, why may not I?</l>
                  <l>But I'le bring <hi>Jaſper</hi> to you ſhall deny all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>What miſchief upon miſchief ſhe deſigns?</l>
                  <l>Doſt think, like thine, my Modeſty is gone?</l>
                  <l>To have this argu'd out before my face</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a Villaine y? —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>A Villain, ſay you?</l>
                  <l>No Villain neither, I wou'd have you know;</l>
                  <l>No more then is <hi>Franciſco:</hi> pick that bone,</l>
                  <l>Or if you will, I'le bid <hi>Gerardo</hi> do it.</l>
                  <l>Dee' think to rail at me? Is that my thanks?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>My feares I ſee will force me to diſſemble;</l>
                  <l>Nurſe, I but try'd thy patience; I believe</l>
                  <l>Thou would'ſt not tell that ſecret for the world;</l>
                  <l>No, tho' it were to <hi>Jaſper.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſper</hi>'s an honeſt fellow, and no Villain;</l>
                  <l>And did he know a ſecret, he could keep it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>But have you told it then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter what I've done, I will not tell you,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe you vext and rated at me ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, Nurſe, I did believe you lov'd me better.</l>
                  <stage>Weeps.</stage>
                  <l>And wou'd truſt me with any thing you did,</l>
                  <l>But I perceive your kindneſs all for <hi>Jaſper.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I love <hi>Jaſper</hi> well, and love you too,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall have no wrong I warrant you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>The thing is plain, I need nor ask no further.</l>
                  <l>But where's the remedy? Nurſe, prethee tell me,</l>
                  <l>What did <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſay unto my meſſage?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I, there's a bus'neſs now worth asking for.</l>
                  <l>He ſayes, he's glad you'l condeſcend to meet;</l>
                  <l>Nay, he's a glad man, I'le tell you that, i'faith;</l>
                  <l>He bid me ſay, you were a gallant Girle,</l>
                  <l>So to Revenge his quarrel on <hi>Gerardo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gerardo,</hi> ſaid you! O thy mouth's a Sieve!</l>
                  <l>There's not a ſecret thou canſt keep a moment;</l>
                  <l>Did I not charge thee not to name <hi>Gerardo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till I ſhould ſpeak of it my ſelf to him?</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:101837:22"/>
                  <l>Nay, 'tis the greateſt motive makes me meet him,</l>
                  <l>For to prevent the miſchiefs elſe may follow;</l>
                  <l>Well, I am curſt for ſin, and thou art made</l>
                  <l>The cauſe o'th' ſin, and curſe that does attend it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>What, are you got to railing again for nothing?</l>
                  <l>Pray who has moſt diſcretion to tell a bus'neſs,</l>
                  <l>You, or I? But you, forſooth, are grown ſo proud of late</l>
                  <l>Becauſe you hope to Marry <hi>Don Gerardo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That there's no ſpeaking to you: Marry gip.</l>
                  <l>'Faith I ſhall ſpoil your Market.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Do thy worſt (for I am reſolv'd to ſuffer once for all)</l>
                  <l>Death would be better then this Slavery,</l>
                  <l>And that's the worſt can happen</l>
                  <l>Should ſhe tell my Brother, or <hi>Gerardo,</hi> my whole ſtory;</l>
                  <l>That's dying once, but I by fear thus fool'd,</l>
                  <l>Do hourly dye, ſince ſtill I Death behold.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Jaſper <hi>and</hi> Antonio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I'm confident this is the Houſe,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Woman Lives I told you of.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Knock then; and if ſhe comes, do you ſpeak to her,</l>
                  <l>I'le ſtand aloof a while, and hear you talk.</l>
                  <stage>Jaſper <hi>knocks.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Witch with a block Rod, which ſhe turns over her Head, whilſt</hi> Jaſper <hi>makes a private ſign of his Lord's being there.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Hail, Reverend Mother; I ſuppoſe you are</l>
                  <l>That famous Artiſt who Commands this Houſe,</l>
                  <l>Which if you be, with confidence I beg,</l>
                  <l>You would reſolve ſome Queſtions I ſhould ask;</l>
                  <l>Which if you pleaſe to do, my gratitude</l>
                  <l>Shall be proportion'd to the kindneſs done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>What prating Fellow's here? Your Lord <hi>Antonio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Need not to doubt my Art, or if he did,</l>
                  <l>He might have ſent ſome wiſer Man to try me.</l>
                  <l>Come, come, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>I am no Cheating Chymiſt, that requires</l>
                  <l>A Faith in Fools to make his work ſucceſsful.</l>
                  <l>No, no, my Power is boundleſs, I can ſearch</l>
                  <l>The ſecrets of your Soul, and when I've done,</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:101837:23"/>
                  <l>Solve all the doubts that there poſſeſs your mind;</l>
                  <l>That Women ſhould be Women, is no wonder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>But that Women ſhould turn Devils, is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, my Lord, I am no Devil neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Mother! I meant not you, when I ſaid ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Son, Son, excuſe it not, you have no cauſe</l>
                  <l>To love us Women much, and I'm not angry</l>
                  <l>At what you ſaid, though I know what you meant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Then, Mother, by theſe Powers you practice by,</l>
                  <l>I do Conjure you, ſhew me all the truth</l>
                  <l>Of what you know concerns my coming hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, enter in, my Lord, and nothing fear;</l>
                  <l>There's not a doubt of yours but ſhall be clear.</l>
                  <l>I've ſent a Spirit out, who will e're long,</l>
                  <l>Bring all the Names of thoſe have done you wrong.</l>
                  <stage>Ex. and return.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio, Jaſper, <hi>and Witch, as in the Houſe; in the Scenes a Chair, by which</hi> Jaſper <hi>ſtands, and Witch goes round.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Sit in this Chair, my Lord, whilſt I do draw</l>
                  <l>A Sacred Line, which ſhall the Spirits aw.</l>
                  <l>About, about, I tread a Round,</l>
                  <l>Where I tread is Sacred Ground.</l>
                  <l>Thus and thus the Air I charm,</l>
                  <l>To keep my Circle free from harm;</l>
                  <l>Thus I ſprinkle Water pure,</l>
                  <l>And by it all the Charm ſecure;</l>
                  <l>The Spirits that fiery are dare not come near us,</l>
                  <l>Earth, Air, and Water do make e'm to fear us.</l>
                  <l>Then boldly ſit, boldly ſee, boldly deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>What Spirits ſoever do happen to riſe.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <stage>Witch ſings.</stage>
                     <l>Riſe, ariſe, ariſe, riſe and come away,</l>
                     <l>My little pretty Spirit <hi>Puncula:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What, not appear at thy Miſtreſſes call,</l>
                     <l>I'le ſurely torment thee; thou ſhalt not ſuck at all.</l>
                     <l>Ariſe then, I ſay —</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Spirit within ſings.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:101837:23"/>
                  <speaker>Spir.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I come, I come away,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Wind it blows hard, and forces me aſtray.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <p>Let's wait a little, he'l appear, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Fear ſeizes me ſo faſt, that all my Spirits</l>
                  <l>Retire, and leave an Ague in my Joynts.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a Spirit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, have you done</l>
                  <l>What I gave you in charge,</l>
                  <l>If you have, I command you to tell it at large.</l>
                  <stage>Spirit ſings.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As you bid, I did go to the Caverns below</l>
                     <l>Where the Spirits Inhabit that Govern the Wind.</l>
                     <l>And though in their motions they be,</l>
                     <l>And ſee</l>
                     <l>Far, far quicker than we,</l>
                     <l>Yet no Intelligence there I could find.</l>
                     <l>From thence, like Lightning, I ſhot to the Pole,</l>
                     <l>Where at a hole</l>
                     <l>I glided to the Region of the Air:</l>
                     <l>But the Spirits above</l>
                     <l>Do Mankind ſo love,</l>
                     <l>That they drove me from them with deſpair.</l>
                     <l>From thence, in a moment, to <hi>Aetna</hi> I came,</l>
                     <l>Where the Spirits of fire that Inhabit that flame:</l>
                     <l>Told me, all that I ſought for they knew;</l>
                     <l>Though to Spirits of Earth,</l>
                     <l>As I am by Birth;</l>
                     <l>They'd not tell it; yet hither they flew.</l>
                     <l>And hereabouts they ſtay, till you pray,</l>
                     <l>And attone them with Offerings to tell your deſire;</l>
                     <l>For theſe from of Old</l>
                     <l>Have been Lovers of Gold,</l>
                     <l>The Mettles being Govern'd by Spirits of fire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>It's neceſſary, Son, you throw them ſomething,</l>
                  <l>For o're theſe Spirits I have no Command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, any thing; take this and throw it them;</l>
                  <l>But do releaſe me of the fear I'm in,</l>
                  <l>And quickly ſolve my doubts, take all I have.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:101837:24"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>There is Gold, there is Gold to you Spirits of fire;</l>
                  <l>He does willingly offer what you do deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter firſt Spirit, ſecond Spirit Aſcends. After ſome flaſhes of fire they ſing.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Spir.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What Spirit did</hi> Lewis <hi>attend?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Spir.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was I.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Spir.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Declare to that Lord what you know.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Spir.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I need not, the cauſe he did dye</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Was that truth to him known long ago.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He's dead, he's dead, he's dead, and now</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For hot deſires,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In endleſs fires</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Muſt Live, muſt now for ever Live with us below.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He's dead, he's dead,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Horrid and wonderful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Spir.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who all</hi> Caelia's <hi>Crimes does know?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Spir.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is I, but muſt not ſhew</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All her ill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For I will</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Third Spirit Aſcends.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fit her better e're ſhe go</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To her Paramour below.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3. Spir.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But I that</hi> Franciſco <hi>attend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Can declare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That he as a Friend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To</hi> Don Lewis <hi>doth ſhare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'th' ſtolen Embraces of</hi> Caelia's <hi>ſweet Arms;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They kiſs and lye down,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then</hi> Lewis <hi>bemoan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus with thoughts of Revenge they double Loves Charms.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They kiſs and lye,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus I have warm'd a Viper in my boſom,</l>
                  <l>That wanted only heat enough to ſting me,</l>
                  <l>And give me Death it ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Spir.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>After him can</hi> Pedro <hi>ſtay til't be day;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus they ſport the Night away,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Flora <hi>watching whilſt they do</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laugh at you,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saying, where's the Cuckold now?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:101837:24"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. Spir.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſport.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. Spir.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They laugh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3. Spir.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They kiſs and play,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till your return, doth make e'm mourn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſpoils their Holy-day.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus they will do untill they dye,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When we in Hell, ſhall think it well</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To have their pleaſant Company.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>They Deſcend.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>And that ſhall be this Night; make ready then</l>
                  <l>Fires that may fit ſo brave a pack of Letchers;</l>
                  <l>If you delight in Offerings; and for Gold</l>
                  <l>Can but increaſe their Torments, I will ſell</l>
                  <l>All my Eſtate to turn it into that,</l>
                  <l>Daily to add more fewel to their flames.</l>
                  <l>Let Fools that ſpend their Wealth on Prieſts for Prayers,</l>
                  <l>Be Cheated ſtill, I'le take a ſurer way,</l>
                  <l>Torments for Souls are penny-worths I'le buy,</l>
                  <l>And there is Reaſon in it; for 'tis likely</l>
                  <l>Hell may take Bribes, when ſurely Heav'n won't.</l>
                  <l>Oh Excellent project! Is't not a good one,
<hi>Jaſper?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By Hell it ſelf, this Night Hell hath e'm all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip's much diſturb'd, I by my Art</l>
                  <l>Will cauſe the Air to give a Melody,</l>
                  <l>So to compoſe your Spirits to themſelves.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>She waves her ſtick. Muſick and an Antick Dance of Devils handing the Purſe</hi> (Antonio <hi>threw</hi>) <hi>to one another, towards the Cloſe of which a noiſe without makes both Muſick and Dance ſtop: But beginning again, a noiſe within makes e'm flye. The Witch trembles.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>Break op'e the doors, nay, ſure enough they're here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>By Heav'n ſome Cheat, for theſe can be no Devils.</l>
                  <l>I'le follow e'm, and ſee —</l>
                  <stage>Draws his Sword.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſome trick to draw you from the Circle.</p>
                  <stage>Jaſp. <hi>holds him.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Be what it will, Death cannot make me worſe;</l>
                  <l>Unhand me then, or I will ſheath this in you.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>O, we're undone, the Officers will enter,</l>
                  <stage>Noiſe continues.</stage>
                  <l>And my Lord will ſee the holes they creep into,</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:101837:25"/>
                  <l>And ſo diſcover them, then we ſhall all be hang'd.</l>
                  <l>I'le tell my Lord the truth of all the Cheat,</l>
                  <l>And that way ſave my Life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>What's that? No ſtratagem to help it?</l>
                  <l>Have you no hole near us, Aunt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, here is one, but ſhould we go into't,</l>
                  <l>The other taken once, will ſoon betray us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I'le hazzard that, rather then certain Death.</l>
                  <l>And therefore to ſave one, I'le hide you there.</l>
                  <stage>Kills her.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Witch.</speaker>
                  <p>O thou ungrateful Dog, doſt kill me for my Love?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>No muttering, Aunt, dye quietly, and lye as</l>
                  <l>Quietly; 'tis the greateſt kindneſs you can</l>
                  <l>Do me: So, now a ready lye clears all I hope.</l>
                  <stage>Runs her through often, then throws her into the hole, ſhe ſhould him, then lyes down and trembles.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>The Officers entring, they all vaniſh'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>The laſt is well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Where's the Witch? What makes you tremble ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>O, do not take me too, good Devil, do not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>What ayls the Fellow? <hi>Jaſper,</hi> don't you know me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, is't you, my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, where's the Witch?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>She got upon a fiery Dragons back,</l>
                  <l>And mounted like a Rocket through the Air,</l>
                  <l>Leaving me half diſtracted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis ſtrange and wonderful.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Captain and Watch.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>VVatch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Here's two of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord <hi>Antonio!</hi> 'Tis ſtrange to meet you thus</l>
                  <l>In a ſuſpitious Houſe ſo late in the Evening.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Riding by the River ſide to take the Air,</l>
                  <l>My Horſe threw me, which made me ſee</l>
                  <l>For ſome convenient Houſe to reſt a while,</l>
                  <l>And met with this, wherein I have ſlept this hour,</l>
                  <l>And I believe had done ſo longer yet,</l>
                  <l>Had not your noiſe awak'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I've no Commiſſion to enquire</l>
                  <l>Into Perſons bus'neſs of your eminent Rank;</l>
                  <l>It is for other Men that I ſearch now,</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:101837:25"/>
                  <l>Some half a ſcore the moſt notorious Rogues</l>
                  <l>About the Town were ſeen to enter here.</l>
                  <l>Saw you none ſuch, my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>No, on my Honour;</l>
                  <l>For ſince I enter'd here, no human ſhape</l>
                  <l>Was ſeen by me, but one Old wither'd Woman;</l>
                  <l>And where ſhe's gone, I know not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, that Woman is the greateſt Cheat</l>
                  <l>About the Town; the ſimple think her a Witch;</l>
                  <l>But I can witneſs for her ſhe is none;</l>
                  <l>My Lord, you'l pardon me, if I ſearch for her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>With all my heart: Pray find her if you can;</l>
                  <l>'Twas my misfortune doubled to light here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>It might have prov'd ſo:</l>
                  <l>Search the Houſe.</l>
                  <stage>Exit VVatch.</stage>
                  <l>I'le tell your Lordſhip what I know of her.</l>
                  <l>Walking my Round one Night, who ſhould I meet,</l>
                  <l>But (as I thought) two Devils, by their ſhapes;</l>
                  <l>An Old one, and a Young one, ſo they ſeem'd:</l>
                  <l>At firſt the ſight amaz'd me, but at laſt</l>
                  <l>My Reaſon telling me, if they were Spirits,</l>
                  <l>The miſchief they intended they might do,</l>
                  <l>Though I ſhould run away: I bid my Guard</l>
                  <l>Stand, whilſt my ſelf advanc'd near theſe ſhapes,</l>
                  <l>Which as I did, the little Devil fled, th' other ſeem'd</l>
                  <l>To turn it's Eyes to fire, and glare upon me;</l>
                  <l>I ſtill advanc'd, Arm'd with my former thoughts,</l>
                  <l>And as I nearer came, the fire grew duller,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill it ſtood, for truly it could not run,</l>
                  <l>Proving, when I laid hold on't, this Old Woman,</l>
                  <l>Cas'd in a Leopard's skin; the fiery Eyes</l>
                  <l>Prov'd but two Lobſter-ſhells: So ſhe confeſſing,</l>
                  <l>That for a Living ſhe did uſe theſe Cheats,</l>
                  <l>Helping poor People to their ſtolen Goods,</l>
                  <l>In Devils ſhapes to countenance the Trade.</l>
                  <l>And that the other was a little Boy,</l>
                  <l>Train'd up as her Familiar, whom ſhe producing,</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:101837:26"/>
                  <l>I only threaten'd them, and let them go.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſubtle Cheat it was, and very likely,</l>
                  <l>And you deſerv'd Reward that did detect it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>A Halter it ſhould be, were I to give it.</p>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter the Watch with one of the Devils Remarkable Habits, and a Viol.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Watch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>We've ſearch'd ſufficiently, but all we find</l>
                  <l>Is a poor Devils skin, and a baſe Viol.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>I, this is like the other, I'm glad 'twas found,</l>
                  <l>'Twill prove the ſtory true I told your Lordſhip.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>It does, to my amazement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm glad it was my hap to meet you here,</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip might have got ſome miſchief elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I might indeed, and I'm beholding to you:</l>
                  <l>And, Captain, take my word, I'le ſpeak your worth</l>
                  <l>To the Vice-Roy, who is my Kinſman,</l>
                  <l>And will take care for to advance your merit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>In that you'l bind my Service: Yet, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Shall I not wait your Lordſhip to your Houſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>No, 'twill be wonder'd at, beſides, I've Horſes here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Health and a good Night attend your Lordſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank you, Captain; here, Watch, there's ſome-</l>
                  <l>Thing for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Watch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs your Noble Lordſhip.</p>
                  <stage>Ex. Capt. and VVatch.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jaſper!</hi> Did you hear this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, my good Lord, and wonder at it too;</l>
                  <l>But I do ſtill believe ſhe is a Witch, and only</l>
                  <l>Did pretend ſuch things to the Captain,</l>
                  <l>To ſave a Burning from th' Inquiſition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Fetch our Horſes.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
                  <l>I do obſerve this Rogue</l>
                  <l>Strangely to be amaz'd, what er'es the matter;</l>
                  <l>I do believe that this was all ſome Cheat.</l>
                  <l>Yet how could that be too, who could Name <hi>Lewis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But I am mad to be deluded thus!</l>
                  <l>For now I think on't better; in my Paſſion</l>
                  <l>I hinted <hi>Lewis</hi> as a proof for all;</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:101837:26"/>
                  <l>And then this Rogue ſtood by — Ay, there it is —</l>
                  <l>He's a Confederate, and contriv'd all this,</l>
                  <l>To be Reveng'd, but I'le diſſemble yet,</l>
                  <l>And trace his miſchiefs further, then I'le kill him,</l>
                  <l>And ſtop his mouth from publiſhing my folly:</l>
                  <l>Had not this Accident ſo ſtrangely happen'd,</l>
                  <l>What miſchief had I done before the Morning:</l>
                  <l>I'le put him to his Tryal in the Garden,</l>
                  <l>Which if he fail in, there ſhall end his Life,</l>
                  <l>And he'l deſerve it too, when miſchiefs tend</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a height, they muſt in miſchief end.</l>
                  <l>He that contriv'd ſo many to deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>Will ſcarce be puniſh'd if he barely dye,</l>
                  <l>Therefore his Villany ſhall further ſwell,</l>
                  <l>When'ts at the height I'le Lanch his Soul to hell.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Franciſco <hi>and</hi> Sebaſtian.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Couzen, believe me, I am loath to go,</l>
                  <l>And I could likewiſe wiſh that you were ſo.</l>
                  <l>Oft have I fear'd the danger when I went,</l>
                  <l>Yet dreaded more the ſin then puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>For I conſider'd, ſhould I then be ſlain,</l>
                  <l>That Death would but begin an endleſs pain;</l>
                  <l>Then pardon me, though I could well obey</l>
                  <l>All Friendſhips Laws, I dare not do't this way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure Couzen, you are ſick, or lately have</l>
                  <l>Had melancholy thoughts about a Grave:</l>
                  <l>Is this <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> he, whoſe ready hand</l>
                  <l>Was quick to Act all Friendſhip did Command?</l>
                  <l>He, who no ſooner heard <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſay,</l>
                  <l>A Danger's there, but made that ſtrait his way,</l>
                  <l>And now he's turn'd my Ghoſtly Father ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I would, ſo I might make a Ghoſtly Cure.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco,</hi> thou art ſick, and ſo am I;</l>
                  <l>Sick at our Souls, and ſhou'd we chance to dye</l>
                  <l>E're our Diſeaſe was Cur'd, 'tis ten to one,</l>
                  <l>We ſhould in an Eternal Feaver groan.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:101837:27"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, prethee ſay no more, 'tis ominous,</l>
                  <l>I wonder much what 'tis ſhou'd make thee thus.</l>
                  <l>Come, you muſt go this Night: I'le tell you why,</l>
                  <l>'Twill be the laſt, for ſhe's to Marry,</l>
                  <l>To Marry <hi>Don Gerardo!</hi> O 'tis rate,</l>
                  <l>I am Reveng'd to th' purpoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure you are</l>
                  <l>Turn'd Coward, or you ne're wou'd glory in</l>
                  <l>Revenge ſo baſe, this doubles all your ſin.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gerardo's</hi> brave, and ſure all Honour bleeds,</l>
                  <l>When ſuch are Wounded by Ignoble deeds.</l>
                  <l>It is the Curſe of Man, that he muſt be</l>
                  <l>Subject to ſhame by Womens Levity;</l>
                  <l>But hold, I wrong <hi>Eugenia,</hi> if I blame</l>
                  <l>Her, and not you alone, for all her ſhame.</l>
                  <l>You Rob'd her of her Chaſtity by force,</l>
                  <l>Though fear of ſhame ſtill kept her from Remorſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Piſh! Force! That was her policy to you,</l>
                  <l>She did no more then what all Women do,</l>
                  <l>Seem to reſiſt what they do moſt deſire,</l>
                  <l>To raiſe the flame, yet ſeem to cool the fire;</l>
                  <l>Believe this Truth, <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> Women can</l>
                  <l>Reſiſt it, and perform it more then Man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus like the Devils we at firſt betray</l>
                  <l>Their Innocence, then blame on them we lay;</l>
                  <l>As if their guilt cou'd have another cauſe</l>
                  <l>Then that which it from our Temptation draws.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Let it be ſo, I'le not diſpute it now;</l>
                  <l>It grows too near the time that I ſhould go,</l>
                  <l>And though my Actions do ſo much offend,</l>
                  <l>I will not doubt to find another Friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you ſo little prize <hi>Eugenia's</hi> Fame,</l>
                  <l>That you can ſuffer more to know her ſhame?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> you miſtake, I do not go</l>
                  <l>This Night on the ſame terms I us'd to do.</l>
                  <l>No, 'tis to take my leave, for ſhe does vow</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of fear ſhe is turn'd vertuous now.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:101837:27"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, then I'le go my ſelf, happen what will,</l>
                  <l>For it is only dang'rous to do ill;</l>
                  <l>My Company her Vertue may protect,</l>
                  <l>And I ſhould ſin, if that I did neglect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>That ſhall not need, for I'm reſolv'd to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>Nothing that may her Reſolution break.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Go boldly then, for in a cauſe ſo good</l>
                  <l>He's more then Coward fears to ſhed his Blood;</l>
                  <l>And though I think <hi>Antonio</hi> would be glad</l>
                  <l>That he our Lives at ſuch advantage had;</l>
                  <l>Yet I this Night durſt boldly meet him there,</l>
                  <l>Since in my Breaſt ſuch Innocence I wear;</l>
                  <l>By this ſecurity I plainly feel</l>
                  <l>'Tis guilt that wounds us deeper far then ſteel.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Caelia <hi>and</hi> Eugenia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Blame not my Husband, Siſter, 'twas my fault,</l>
                  <l>I ſtrove 'gainſt Reaſon to oppoſe his Will.</l>
                  <l>Had I forborn my importunity,</l>
                  <l>'Tis ten to one he had not been ſo wilful;</l>
                  <l>Husband's prerogatives are abſolute,</l>
                  <l>Their wills we muſt obey, and not diſpute.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>I beg his Pardon, if I think amiſs,</l>
                  <l>But I believe there's ſome deſign in this;</l>
                  <l>His Eyes ſhew'd more of Anger then could be</l>
                  <l>A bare concern for's Friend's Infirmity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>I will no cenſure on his Actions lay,</l>
                  <l>My Duty is for their ſucceſs to pray.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Don Gerardo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Servant, Ladies, where is <hi>Don Antonio?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, at <hi>Don Johns,</hi> my Lord, do not you know it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Then he is not come back, as I had thought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, why thought you ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I did not know but that he might,</l>
                  <l>Since 'tis not five hours bus'neſs to Ride thither,</l>
                  <l>And to return again; but, Madam, pray</l>
                  <l>How came the Lord <hi>Franciſco</hi> to be here?</l>
                  <l>I think he does not uſe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:101837:28"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Franciſco!</hi> O my fears!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>No ſure, my Lord, he ne're came within theſe doors</l>
                  <l>Since my good Father dy'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure I'm miſtaken, Madam, if I did not</l>
                  <l>Meet him juſt now as he came forth this Room:</l>
                  <l>And more, he ſhak'd his head in Anger at me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm ſure, my Lord, you're miſtaken much,</l>
                  <l>For you're the firſt that enter'd here but us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>It may be I'm miſtaken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſure, my Lord, you are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, if your Commands</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Eugenia.</stage>
                  <l>Extend to any thing within my pow'r, pray name it,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be proud to ſerve you; elſe I'm gone,</l>
                  <l>For I have certain bus'neſs does require it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>The greateſt Service you can do to me,</l>
                  <l>Is to be careful of your ſelf, my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>This kindneſs doth oblige me, pardon my haſte,</l>
                  <l>Good Night, and Reſt unto your Ladyſhips.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Night, my Lord;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flora</hi> is ſo poſſeſt her Dream is true,</l>
                  <l>She dare not venture in that Room again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>She is not ſuch a Fool, ſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, Siſter, I am not well, and will to Bed;</l>
                  <l>The Nurſe will wait on you, I'le ſend her to you.</l>
                  <l>Come, <hi>Flora,</hi> go with me.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Cael. <hi>and</hi> Flora.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, good Reſt unto you.</l>
                  <l>This I can wiſh to her, whilſt I muſt want it:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gerardo</hi> ſure has ſome Intelligence</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Don Franciſco</hi>'s coming to me;</l>
                  <l>Or elſe why Nam'd he him, for well he knows</l>
                  <l>He never us'd to make a Viſit here:</l>
                  <l>Well, if he does, I cannot help it now.</l>
                  <l>The time draws nigh,</l>
                  <l>That I muſt meet <hi>Franciſco!</hi> Oh, that word</l>
                  <l>Gives heavineſs a new unto my Soul,</l>
                  <l>And makes my thoughts run backwards,</l>
                  <l>The Accidents oth' day ſeems Ominous</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:101837:28"/>
                  <l>To all the Houſe, but moſt of all to me,</l>
                  <l>My guilty Breaſt feels moſt of miſery.</l>
                  <l>This time will quickly over, then I ſhall</l>
                  <l>See what they tend to, or not ſee at all.</l>
                  <l>"There's comfort yet, that miſeries at height</l>
                  <l>"Loſe their firſt property, which is to fright.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>The End of the Third Act.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Act the Fourth.</head>
               <stage>Caelia <hi>on a Couch,</hi> Flora <hi>by her.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FLora,</hi> I cannot ſleep, for all my thoughts</l>
                  <l>Infected with my griefs, flye up and down,</l>
                  <l>Collecting only things to keep me waking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                  <p>I'le not ſtir from you, Madam, 'all this Night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flora,</hi> thy diligence deſerves Reward,</l>
                  <l>And I'le not long be backward for to thank thee.</l>
                  <l>But prethee ſing that Song I love ſo well,</l>
                  <l>That harmony, perhaps, will Charm my cares,</l>
                  <l>And give my ſenſes Reſt.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <head>The Song.</head>
                     <head type="sub">1.</head>
                     <stage>Flor. ſings.</stage>
                     <l>AH, <hi>Choridon,</hi> in vain you boaſt,</l>
                     <l>You ſtill do <hi>Cloris</hi> Love;</l>
                     <l>For better 'tis your heart were loſt,</l>
                     <l>Then thus ſuſpitious prove:</l>
                     <l>You then would kill me by diſdain,</l>
                     <l>But dying thus you blot my Name.</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:101837:29"/>
                     <l>For all will ſay</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cloris</hi> was falſe, and went aſtray;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cloris</hi> was falſe, and did deſerve her ſhame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>For happy Shepherd, well you know,</l>
                     <l>Your Fame does mine excell;</l>
                     <l>All Gen'rous <hi>Choridons</hi> do know,</l>
                     <l>But none my Tale can tell:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cloris,</hi> though true, muſt loſe that Name,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Choridon</hi> will keep his Fame;</l>
                     <l>For all will ſay</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cloris</hi> was falſe, and went aſtray,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cloris</hi> was falſe, and did deſerve her ſhame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>But Cruel Shepherd, when you hear</l>
                     <l>That I am dead indeed,</l>
                     <l>I do believe you'l ſhed a tear,</l>
                     <l>Though now you have decreed,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Cloris</hi> true muſt loſe that Name,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Choridon</hi> to keep his Fame;</l>
                     <l>And then you'l ſay</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cloris</hi> was true, and ne're did ſtray;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cloris</hi> was true, and I deſerve her ſhame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                  <l>She's faln aſleep, may none but happy Dreams</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſs her Fancy.</l>
                  <stage>The Scene ſhuts.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio <hi>and</hi> Jaſper <hi>in the Garden.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>Your confidence in this doth much amaze me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, ſtill I'le pawn my Life, that what I ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Appears e're long a truth Infallible,</l>
                  <l>And your own Eyes will bear me witneſs of it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, pitch upon a private ſtand for us,</l>
                  <l>That you know moſt convenient.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Jaſp.</stage>
                  <l>Strange it is,</l>
                  <l>If this ſhould prove a falſhood after this;</l>
                  <l>I've threaten'd him with Death upon the failer,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill he has perſiſted to affirm it,</l>
                  <l>Beſides, I climb'd the Garden Wall before him,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:101837:29"/>
                  <l>And that way gave him time for his eſcape,</l>
                  <l>If he'd deſign to make it: Theſe Circumſtances</l>
                  <l>Do half perſwade 'tis true. Oh, apprehenſion!</l>
                  <l>So terrible the conſequence appears,</l>
                  <l>It makes my brain turn round, and Night ſeem darker.</l>
                  <l>The Moon begins to drown her ſelf in Clouds,</l>
                  <l>Leaving a duskiſh horror every where,</l>
                  <l>My ſickly fancy makes the Garden ſeem</l>
                  <l>Like thoſe benighted Groves in <hi>Pluto's</hi> Kingdoms,</l>
                  <l>Which Poets fancy that the damn'd Inhabit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, my Lord.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>What now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>The Garden Door juſt opens, ſtep this way, leſt</l>
                  <l>You be ſeen.</l>
                  <stage>They ſtand cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Franciſco <hi>and</hi> Sebaſtian.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis hardly late enough, we'l ſtay a little,</l>
                  <l>For I perceive no light i'th' uſual Window.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt,</speaker>
                  <p>But are you confident <hi>Antonio's</hi> abſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm told for certain that he went from home</l>
                  <l>To ſee <hi>Don John Valaſco,</hi> who is ſick.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, then with ſafety we may walk a turn,</l>
                  <l>Though I confeſs, do what I can, my fears</l>
                  <l>Surmount my Reaſon, and perſwades there's danger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>A hundred times I've paſt it in as much,</l>
                  <l>Yet then with confidence you ſlighted all;</l>
                  <l>Prethee forbear to urge them any more;</l>
                  <l>I'm half turn'd Coward with your fears already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's take a turn then further from the Houſe,</l>
                  <l>And by ſome other talk divert our thoughts.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſper,</hi> I find thy Informations true,</l>
                  <l>Thus far at leaſt; theſe are my Wife's kind Couzens.</l>
                  <l>Hell rid e'm from the World.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>A hundred times they had been here before</l>
                  <l>In as much danger: Mark you that, my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I, and his Soul retorted back the Lye,</l>
                  <l>For they in all their Lives ne're knew a danger</l>
                  <l>Equal to that they're near: Heark! how the Owl</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:101837:30"/>
                  <l>Summons their Souls to take a flight with her,</l>
                  <l>Where they ſhall be Eternally benighted:</l>
                  <l>Now I again believe it was a Witch;</l>
                  <l>For here me-thinks I ſee a thouſand Devils</l>
                  <l>Waiting in the Air with fire-forks in their hands,</l>
                  <l>Juſt as our City Serjeants wait with Maces,</l>
                  <l>To toſs their Souls to their Eternal Priſon;</l>
                  <l>Look there, that flaſh of Lightning does confirm it.</l>
                  <l>Nay, do but ſtay a little, you ſhall have all.</l>
                  <l>All, all; not a Soul of e'm ſhall eſcape this Night.</l>
                  <l>No, no, 'twill ſpoil good Company to part them.</l>
                  <l>But hold, a Light appears, draw back to cover.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Franciſco <hi>and</hi> Sebaſtian.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The Light is there, make haſte and give the ſign.</p>
                  <stage>Franciſco <hi>ſtrikes a Key upon his Sword;</hi> Eugenia <hi>appears above in</hi> Caelia's <hi>Gown.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Who's there, <hi>Franciſco?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſame, and would deſire your Company below.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>This diſtance fits us better! Oh, <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had we but alwayes kept it, I had been</l>
                  <l>A ſpotleſs Off'ring to my Bridal Bed,</l>
                  <l>But now muſt cloud my Marriage Joys with ſhame,</l>
                  <l>And fear of what will follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray deſcend, this diſtance is not ſafe,</l>
                  <l>The Family may chance o're hear our words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>I've more cauſe, ſhould I come down,</l>
                  <l>You would attempt my ſtrength, and Argument</l>
                  <l>To violate my Vows, as firſt you did</l>
                  <l>My Virgin-Honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>No, upon my Life, do but deſcend,</l>
                  <l>And may the Heav'ns pour all their Vengeance on me</l>
                  <l>If I do attempt you with a ſillable</l>
                  <l>To break your Reſolution.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Is any with you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, my Friend, <hi>Sebaſtian.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Let him ſpeak, then.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:101837:30"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, upon my Life, I will ſecure you,</l>
                  <l>And glory I have ſo much cauſe to do it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Virtue I rely on for my ſafety.</p>
                  <stage>She takes the Light from above.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio <hi>and</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot hear their words, yet I'm ſure</l>
                  <l>It's <hi>Caelia's</hi> there, her Habit tells me that.</l>
                  <l>Let's draw a little nearer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Look there, <hi>Franciſco,</hi> are not thoſe two Men</l>
                  <l>Are creeping there?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis ſo, let's ſlip aſide.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Fran. <hi>and</hi> Sebaſtian.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Eugenia <hi>below.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <p>Where are you, Couzen <hi>Franciſco?</hi> Are you there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <p>I, here, here, perfidious Woman.</p>
                  <stage>Stabs her, ſhe falls.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Franciſco,</hi> 'tis an inhuman deed,</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Ant. Jaſp.</stage>
                  <l>To kill me thus, 'cauſe I would ſin no longer,</l>
                  <l>But thou haſt kept thy word, and took thy leave.</l>
                  <l>As I muſt now, of all the World, and thee — oh, oh —</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Gerardo <hi>hand Servant.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Heav'n I be'n't too late, the Garden door</l>
                  <l>So open makes me wonder: Heard you no groans?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>I think I did, my Lord; heark, Sir again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, oh; I fain would live a little longer,</l>
                  <l>If but to ask forgiveneſs of <hi>Gerardo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Soul will ſcarce reach Heav'n without his Pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that wou'd go to Heav'n, and wants my Pardon?</l>
                  <l>Take it, what e're thou art, and mayſt thou be</l>
                  <l>Happy in Death, what e're thou didſt deſign.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Is that <hi>Gerardo's</hi> Voyce? Sure loſs of Blood</l>
                  <l>Doth make my fancy Idle: Is't <hi>Gerardo?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou greateſt Bleſſing of my Soul, it is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, my Lord, you will abhor my Name,</l>
                  <l>When I ſhall tell the ſtory made me thus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Heav'n knows I ſooner ſhould abhor my Life:</l>
                  <l>But tell me the Author of this horrid miſchief,</l>
                  <l>That I may flye as quick to my Revenge,</l>
                  <l>As theſe ſad thoughts do ſeize upon thy Soul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>When you ſhall hear my ſtory, your Revenge</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:101837:31"/>
                  <l>Will, as I fear, vent againſt me in Curſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Were thy Crimes great as theirs that left thee thus,</l>
                  <l>By all thy Virgin hopes I would not Curſe thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, that's it you are deceiv'd in.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, now thou rav'ſt — help me to bend her body</l>
                  <l>Her loſs of Blood will keep her ſtory from me;</l>
                  <l>And I ſhall Live i'th' dark, and ne're Revenge her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, my Lord, my Couzen, baſe <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Being let in by my accurſed Nurſe,</l>
                  <l>Came to my bed, and there by force and ſtrength obtain'd</l>
                  <l>His hated ends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, damn'd Villain, he ſhall not long ſurvive</l>
                  <l>To boaſt of it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>Had I ſtaid there, and not conſented further,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould have needed pity, and not pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Tell all the reſt, for this is ſo ſurprizing,</l>
                  <l>I'd fain perſwade my ſelf it was a Dream.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>After this Fatal loſs, a ſhame ſucceeded,</l>
                  <l>Shame that produc'd fear; infus'd by threats</l>
                  <l>Urg'd both by him and her, wherein they ſaid,</l>
                  <l>If I refus'd to grant that willingly,</l>
                  <l>Which he at firſt did force, they would declare</l>
                  <l>The Action to the World, ſo to diſgrace me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>O that old wrinkl'd Hag! that ſhe ſhould plot this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>What will not wicked Age effect for Gold?</l>
                  <l>But they at laſt made fear or'e-come my Vertue,</l>
                  <l>And I by that made all their guilt my own,</l>
                  <l>Meeting him here ſtill when he did appoint.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, this confeſt, how came you by theſe Wounds?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, <hi>Franciſco</hi> did entreat my Company</l>
                  <l>This Night; when as I enter'd,</l>
                  <l>Without a word, but here, perfidious Woman,</l>
                  <l>He ſtab'd me in the Breaſt, and left me thus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Hadſt thou been dead, and Angels told the ſtory,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould have thought, in Envy of thy worth,</l>
                  <l>They had invented it, and ne're believ'd it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
                  <l>I have no breath to tell you; oh, my Lord,</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:101837:31"/>
                  <l>I do forget, they ſtill are in the Garden —</l>
                  <l>Have a care of —</l>
                  <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Have a care of what? Oh, ſpeak, <hi>Eugenia,</hi> ſpeak.</l>
                  <l>She's gone, ſhe's gone; and could not tell her mind:</l>
                  <l>What is't I muſt have a care on! O ſome Angel</l>
                  <l>That waits to ſhew her Soul the way to Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>Come back and tell me, what it was ſhe meant:</l>
                  <l>Was it her Reputation ſhe took care of?</l>
                  <l>No, no, that cannot be, had it been that,</l>
                  <l>She might have kept the ſtory to her ſelf:</l>
                  <l>And there been Canoniz'd: Was it of me</l>
                  <l>She did expreſs her care? If ſo, 'twas needleſs;</l>
                  <l>For he that lets me Live to kill <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though he does ſo by me, when that is done,</l>
                  <l>Shall have my thanks and Prayers i'th' other World;</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, they're in the Garden, I'le go look e'm,</l>
                  <l>"For if Revenge ſo juſt I do delay,</l>
                  <l>"I ſhall deſerve Heav'ns Vengeance for the ſtay.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Franciſco <hi>and</hi> Sebaſtian.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Who ſhould they be I wonder talk'd ſo long?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure, when ſhe found us not, ſhe would retire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>No doubt on't; yet I am not ſatisfy'd what two</l>
                  <l>Thoſe were, and why they ſtaid ſo long.</l>
                  <l>Could your Ear reach to underſtand their words?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>No, not a ſyllable more then a humming noiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor mine; but now they're gone, let's walk that way,</l>
                  <l>'Twill be the beſt to miſs them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Content.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Don Gerardo <hi>and Servant.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>It is in vain to look e'm if they hide,</l>
                  <l>The Garden's large; beſides perhaps they're gone;</l>
                  <l>We'l to the Body.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>You're by it now, my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>This Accident amazes me ſo much,</l>
                  <l>I go I know not where.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:101837:32"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Franciſco <hi>and</hi> Sebaſtian.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>See there, my Lord, two Men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>W'are pretty near the Window, there's no Light.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Have at thy heart, <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Ger. <hi>and Servant draw.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>This Token from <hi>Eugenia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, then, at thine: Be whom thou wilt, that Name</l>
                  <l>Tells me thou'rt no Friend.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They Fight, the Servant ſhoots</hi> Sebaſtian
<hi>juſt as</hi> Franciſco <hi>ruas</hi> Gerardo <hi>through, which purſuing, Servant kills him too.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Courage, <hi>Sebaſtian's</hi> by thee.</l>
                  <l>My fears are come about, for I am kill'd;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco,</hi> fare thee well.</l>
                  <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis double Death to ſee my Friend dye thus.</l>
                  <l>Was't not enough, you Fates, to take my Life,</l>
                  <l>But I muſt guilty be of murd'ring him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, how do you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Making what haſte I can to meet <hi>Eugenia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>O me! Unfortunate!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Bewail me not; Death is a pleaſure to me,</l>
                  <l>Since I can ſee <hi>Franciſco</hi> lye there by me;</l>
                  <l>But ask him e're I dye,</l>
                  <l>What made him kill <hi>Eugenia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>What, is <hi>Eugenia</hi> Dead?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſeems it ſtrange to thee, who baſely haſt</l>
                  <l>Firſt Rob'd her of her Honour, then of Life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gerardo,</hi> it was cruelty to kill her, being as</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhe had not done thee wrong, and dying,</l>
                  <l>I rejoyce I have Reveng'd her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco,</hi> ſure thy Crimes have made thee Devil,</l>
                  <l>Or thou would'ſt ne're transfer thy Treachery</l>
                  <l>By murd'ring her, and place it thus on me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>May I reach Heav'n as I'm Innocent</l>
                  <l>Of any Death but yours: Which if a guilt</l>
                  <l>Forgive me Heav'n and you as —</l>
                  <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>He's dead, my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>With ſuch a Lye in's mouth;</l>
                  <l>O Heavenly Angels lead me not this way,</l>
                  <l>For he muſt alwayes walk i'th' paths of falſhood;</l>
                  <l>Remove me nearer to <hi>Eugenia's</hi> Body;</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:101837:32"/>
                  <l>My Spirits faint apace, and I muſt follow:</l>
                  <l>One word, and then farewell;</l>
                  <l>I have no time for to Reward thy care:</l>
                  <l>Here, take this Ring, and give it to my Brother,</l>
                  <l>He left it with me when he went to Travel;</l>
                  <l>Tell him I ſtill preſerv'd it for his ſake,</l>
                  <l>A faithful pledge of our United Friendſhip.</l>
                  <l>Bid him, that by this Token he believes</l>
                  <l>Three words I left within my Cabinet</l>
                  <l>Concerning thee this Evening: He will do it,</l>
                  <l>And uſe thee as a Friend, as I have done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>I'le bear the Ring, but not the Meſſage, Sir;</l>
                  <l>I ne're will ſeek for Friends when you are gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ger.</speaker>
                  <l>I do conjure thee do it: Tell our ſtory too</l>
                  <l>As true as is thy ſelf: But have a care,</l>
                  <l>Wound not <hi>Eugenia</hi>'s Fame more then muſt needs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco</hi>'s and <hi>Eugenia's</hi> dying words</l>
                  <l>Will make it ſtrangely dark, as 'tis to me,</l>
                  <l>But I muſt leave it ſo!</l>
                  <l>Give me thy hand, commend me to <hi>Antonio;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alas! I had forgot him, pray Heav'n his ſtory</l>
                  <l>Produce no further miſchief; tell <hi>Caelia</hi> nothing</l>
                  <l>Befor't be day: Bus'neſs comes thronging on me,</l>
                  <l>But I faint — make but one Grave, and lay us</l>
                  <l>In it thus — Farewell.</l>
                  <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Now dyes the juſteſt Man the Earth contains,</l>
                  <l>And I would do ſo too, but that I know</l>
                  <l>Self-murderers ne're muſt keep him Company;</l>
                  <l>I'le ſet the Bodies up againſt the Wall,</l>
                  <l>And call the Watch; what if they ſay I'm guilty,</l>
                  <l>And make my Life to anſwer all theſe Deaths:</l>
                  <l>Why, let e'm do't, for Death would now be well</l>
                  <l>Since to ſurvive his loſs to me's a Hell.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio <hi>and</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come, my Lord, the coaſt is quiet now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope that Piſtol ſav'd our ſwords a labour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm ſure they could not leave the Garden yet,</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:101837:33"/>
                  <l>But we muſt needs have ſeem e'm.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, I'm ſure they did not paſs the Garden door,</l>
                  <l>For if they had, we ſhould have ſtopt their Journey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I think I heard a talking up this way,</l>
                  <l>After the Piſtol made us leave our Poſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Though I did leave the Door, yet ſtill my Eye</l>
                  <l>Was bent that way, and I ſaw none to paſs.</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, where's <hi>Caelia</hi>'s Body?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>See, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>There is a Man doth hold her in his Arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>It is <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſure! Have at his heart.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Runs at</hi> Gerardo.</stage>
                  <l>How's this, not ſtir! Nay, then he's dead</l>
                  <l>Already — the Moon deceives me, or it is
<hi>Gerardo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh Heav'n's! It is my Friend, dead, dead, and ſtiff,</l>
                  <l>And my accurſed hand hath Wounded him.</l>
                  <l>This is not <hi>Caelia</hi> neither, but <hi>Eugenia</hi> in her Gown!</l>
                  <l>What ſtrange miſtakes are theſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>But who are here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>What, more!</l>
                  <l>By Heav'ns <hi>Franciſco</hi> and his Friend
<hi>Sebaſtian!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both dead too! Death has had a Feaſt to Night.</l>
                  <l>Do not we Dream? As for this Womans Death,</l>
                  <l>Surely her Fathers Soul did guide my hand</l>
                  <l>To ſtrike the blow, ſince needs ſhe muſt betray</l>
                  <l>Her Honour to <hi>Franciſco,</hi> in theſe meetings!</l>
                  <l>But oh, my Sword hath pierc'd my Friend <hi>Gerardo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What Fatal Accident mixt his Blood with theirs.</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, there's Light appears, ſlip into the Grotto.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant, Captain, and Watch, with two Torches.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Here is the diſmal place I told you of,</l>
                  <l>And here the Bodies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſight moſt terrible in time of Peace!</l>
                  <l>But did <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſtill deny her Death?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>To his laſt moment;</l>
                  <l>He did confeſs he had abus'd her,</l>
                  <l>But would have plac'd her Death upon my Lord.</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:101837:33"/>
                  <l>And ſeem'd as much to wonder we deny'd it</l>
                  <l>As we that he did ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſaid <hi>Sebaſtian?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſcarce did ſpeak a word after I ſhot him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Had we not beſt to knock, and call <hi>Antonio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>He's not at Home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, but I'm ſure he is.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>He was not late at Night, for I was there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>That's ſtrange, for juſt at ſhutting in o'th' Evening</l>
                  <l>I met him at a Houſe that ſtands i'th' Suburbs,</l>
                  <l>Saying, he would go Home.</l>
                  <l>I think however we had beſt to knock.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>My dying Lord made it his laſt deſire,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Caelia</hi> might not be diſturb'd this Night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, take the Bodies up, and keep e'm ſafe,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall to the Vice-Roy's preſently with me,</l>
                  <l>I ſcarce perform my truſt, if I detain</l>
                  <l>The knowledge of ſo ſtrange an Accident</l>
                  <l>A moment from his Ears, whoſe Wiſdom will</l>
                  <l>Direct in this, which far exceeds my skill.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Antonio <hi>and</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſee, my Lord, that I was in the right,</l>
                  <l>I only ſaid, it was my Ladies Gown,</l>
                  <l>But never did affirm it was her Perſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>And I am glad it is not: Now, if Nurſe</l>
                  <l>Fails too in her diſcovery, I am ſafe;</l>
                  <l>For if we keep our Councel, all theſe Deaths</l>
                  <l>Lye pat amongſt themſelves, and there's not one,</l>
                  <l>Except <hi>Gerardo,</hi> that I'd wiſh alive;</l>
                  <l>He was my friend, and it looks Ominous,</l>
                  <l>That I ſhould Wound him ſo, though after Death:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jaſper,</hi> thy diligence ſhan't want Reward,</l>
                  <l>But that muſt follow: Come, let's away.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>My Reward follows! I believe it does;</l>
                  <l>'Faith, my good Lord, be ſure it be a good one,</l>
                  <l>Or be content to hang for Company;</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:101837:34"/>
                  <l>Now hap what will, I'le rid him with this murther;</l>
                  <l>Till I do make him ſpend's Eſtate to Bribe me:</l>
                  <l>"I was his Slave before for fear; but now</l>
                  <l>"I'le make him mine, ſince I this ſecret know.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>The End of the Fourth Act.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Act the Fifth.</head>
               <stage>Caelia <hi>Diſcover'd in Bed,</hi> Flora <hi>by her.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>SUre 'twas a real Piſtol-ſhot that wak'd me,</l>
                  <l>Yet from a Dream ſo terrible, it did it,</l>
                  <l>That I had rather never ſleep again,</l>
                  <l>Then hazzard ſuch another: I thought I ſaw</l>
                  <l>Lye dead by me,</l>
                  <l>My Lord <hi>Antonio, Don Gerardo, Jaſper,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Nurſe, <hi>Franciſco,</hi> and the Young
<hi>Sebaſtian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Pedro,</hi> and thy ſelf; this dreadful ſight,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe the Piſtols noiſe, I ſpoke of, wak'd me,</l>
                  <l>And made me cry help, help, which frighted thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Why truly, Madam, it was a dreadful Dream,</l>
                  <l>And I as much was frighted at your call,</l>
                  <l>Yet, for my own part, I did hear no Piſtol.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>It may be then, it only was my fancy,</l>
                  <l>For truly all my Dream ſeems ſtill to me</l>
                  <l>So like a truth, that I can ſcarce diſtinguiſh</l>
                  <l>Whether I then did wake, or now am ſleeping;</l>
                  <l>And but I ſee theſe things, and thee ſo plain,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould conclude my Dream did ſtill continue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Heav'n divert all miſchief from the houſe,</l>
                  <l>For I have heard it ſaid by Learned Men,</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:101837:34"/>
                  <l>Nay, and Religious too, that Dreams like theſe,</l>
                  <l>That ſtick ſo faſt upon our fancies waking,</l>
                  <l>Are guided by a power that's more then Chance,</l>
                  <l>And alwayes are portents of ſomething like them:</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure, for my own part, do what I can,</l>
                  <l>That Dream I had will not yet leave my head,</l>
                  <l>Which makes me think <hi>Jaſper</hi> deſigns me miſchief.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flora,</hi> you go too far, Dreams are but ſhadows</l>
                  <l>Reflected from ſome Acts the day preceeding,</l>
                  <l>As ours are now; for from thoſe Accidents</l>
                  <l>Of my Lords taking <hi>Jaſper,</hi> the Dream you told,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Don Gerardo's</hi> naming of <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mine now is formed: Thus they but ſucceed</l>
                  <l>Things paſt, and not prognoſtick things to come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Heav'ns theſe do not do't, but I'm afraid.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Nurſe, frighted with</hi> Eugenia's
<hi>Ghoſt.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand off, ſtand off, what makes you follow me?</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure I did not kill you, if you're dead,</l>
                  <l>Or if you be not, why are you ſo pale?—</l>
                  <l>So, ſo — ſhe's gone — but what made me come hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>What, do you ſtudy wayes to fright me, Nurſe?</l>
                  <l>It is no proper time to play your tricks.</l>
                  <l>What makes you up at ſuch a time of Night?</l>
                  <l>Look, how ſhe ſtands amaz'd, and doth not anſwer;</l>
                  <l>Think you I take a pleaſure to be frighted?</l>
                  <l>That you perſiſt in't ſtill?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>What, is the Woman mad, or would be thought ſo?</l>
                  <l>What makes you ſtand and ſtare thus?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Did you ſee no Body?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Who ſhould we ſee but an Old doting fool,</l>
                  <l>That turn'd a Child again, would Act like one,</l>
                  <l>And can't find a proper time for't neither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>What make you up ſo late, Nurſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>What's that to you? It may be I ſat up</l>
                  <l>To make my Lady merry with this Jeſt,</l>
                  <l>But now, forſooth, I'm grown too Old to pleaſe her.</l>
                  <l>You are her favourite — what, come again?</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:101837:35"/>
                  <l>O, do not ſtare ſo at me!</l>
                  <stage>Shreeks.</stage>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>There's ſomething more in this then barely play!</l>
                  <l>How the Old VVoman ſtar'd? ſure ſhe's run mad!</l>
                  <l>For ſhame, or ſorrow <hi>Jaſper</hi> goes away.</l>
                  <l>Prethee follow her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Since you will have me, Madam, I will do't,</l>
                  <l>Though I dare ſcarcely venture.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>The greateſt Object pity hath, is Age,</l>
                  <l>When it returns to Childiſhneſs again,</l>
                  <l>As this Old Woman doth; and though we ſay,</l>
                  <l>That Age is Honourable, we only mean,</l>
                  <l>When Gravity and Wiſdom are its marks,</l>
                  <l>And not gray hairs, and froward peeviſhneſs,</l>
                  <l>As ten for one, are known by to be Old,</l>
                  <l>And though we ſee this true, yet we would all</l>
                  <l>Prolong our time to that decrepid ſtate,</l>
                  <l>When nothing but contempt can wait upon us;</l>
                  <l>How ſtrangely ſin daſtards our very Reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Making that guide us to deſire known ills</l>
                  <l>Rather then Joys, that promis'd we deſerve not;</l>
                  <l>For the beſt Men through ſenſe of guilt do fear</l>
                  <l>To change for unſeen Joys their troubles here.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>If this Ghoſt follow ſtill, 'twill make me mad;</l>
                  <l>For ſure it is a Ghoſt it looks ſo pale;</l>
                  <l>Ay, and <hi>Eugenia</hi>'s Ghoſt, I'm ſure it is;</l>
                  <l>But who ſhould kill her? May be <hi>Don Franciſco!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh, there it is again — It's not my fault —</l>
                  <l>Oh, do not follow me then: What ſhall I do?</l>
                  <l>See there again, ſhe points unto her Breaſts —</l>
                  <l>It's gone again, I fear 'twill make me mad —</l>
                  <l>I'le go to Prayers: But I forget my bus'neſs,</l>
                  <l>My Lord will come, and I muſt let him in,</l>
                  <l>And ſhew him what I promis'd, or he'l kill me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Flora.</stage>
                  <l>What, come again! Oh, Heav'ns! I'le ſtop my Eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Nurſe, are you mad?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:101837:35"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>No, you would make me ſo! But I deſie thee —</l>
                  <l>Be gone, thou Spirit, i'th' name of Heav'n, be gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Who ſhould be gone?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou! for thou'rt the Devil. Come not near me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lady ſent me to you —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, ſhe did not, for ſhe lov'd me always,</l>
                  <l>And would not ſend the Devil thus to fright me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>I am no Devil, Nurſe, look upon me, I'm <hi>Flora.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, where's the Spirit then I ſaw juſt now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>There was no worſer Spirit then my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>No; 'pray Minx, what makes you follow me?</l>
                  <l>I'le ſet you back again i'th' Devils Name,</l>
                  <l>Come you to ſpy my Actions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>No, Nurſe, my Lady ſent me, don't be angry,</l>
                  <l>She was afraid that you were running mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I, mad, it may be ſo; now I am Old</l>
                  <l>I muſt be mad, forſooth; but time has been,</l>
                  <l>There's ne're a Servant durſt have laught at me,</l>
                  <l>Nor I'le not take it now, no that I won't,</l>
                  <l>I'le tear your Eyes out firſt.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>She runs after</hi> Flora, <hi>who ſtill is too quick for her.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, ſoftly, Nurſe; ſo, ſo; ay, there!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Where, where? I ſee it now, It's ſtrangely pale!</l>
                  <l>O, do not fright me ſo; it's gone again.</l>
                  <l>And now I ſhall have time to follow you;</l>
                  <l>Nay, now I'le tear thy Eyes out.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>As</hi> Flora <hi>runs away, ſhe falls, Nurſe gets upon her</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, Nurſe, Nurſe! have mercy on me,</l>
                  <l>Do not ſcratch me ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I'le be thy Death, there's nothing ſhall preſerve you.</l>
                  <l>Ah — are you there again! The Devil, the Devil.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas well for me her madneſs work't again,</l>
                  <l>And made her take a whim to run away,</l>
                  <l>She would have kill'd me elſe, do what I could;</l>
                  <l>I'le ſtay no longer, leſt ſhe come again.</l>
                  <l>I'd not be in her fingers as I was</l>
                  <l>For all I'm worth.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:101837:36"/>
               <stage>Enter Captain, Watch, and Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>When I conſider every Circumſtance</l>
                  <l>Of what you tell, and what I know my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>I muſt conclude, I ought not to defer</l>
                  <l>To ſearch <hi>Antonio</hi>'s Houſe: if he's from home,</l>
                  <l>As you pretend he is: It makes me think</l>
                  <l>There is ſome ſtrange Intrigue deſign'd by him.</l>
                  <l>For why ſhould he turn back, as you relate,</l>
                  <l>And then obſcure himſelf in ſuch a Houſe?</l>
                  <l>Beſides, he told me, he was ſtrait for Home,</l>
                  <l>And yet it ſeems he was not, as you ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>It's truth, upon my Life, he was not there</l>
                  <l>At paſt the hour of Nine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Watch.</speaker>
                  <l>Who comes there!</l>
                  <stage>Enter the little Devil, and runs and skulkes.</stage>
                  <l>Captain, the Devil, the Devil!</l>
                  <l>See where he ſtands?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>O'my Conſcience! The Witches little Familiar again!</l>
                  <l>If you're afraid, let me come, I'm us'd to</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſort of Devils! Come, come, uncaſe,</l>
                  <stage>It ſputters like a Cat, Captain to him.</stage>
                  <l>Uncaſe, young Gameſter, what ſlippery pranck</l>
                  <l>Are you about now? Don't you remember your</l>
                  <l>Laſt eſcape, Sirrah?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devil.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Maſter don't whip me, I'le tell all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Out with it then; where's the Old Witch, your Miſtreſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devil.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, Captain, ſhe was kill'd to Night when</l>
                  <l>You brought in the Watch to ſearch our Houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Kill'd, by whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devil.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not that, but we were putting a cheat</l>
                  <l>Upon a Lord there, by contrivance of his Man,</l>
                  <l>And when you knockt, we ran to our lurking holes</l>
                  <l>To hide us, but when the Coaſt was clear, we came</l>
                  <l>Out, and ſeeking for my Miſtreſs, found her dead in one</l>
                  <l>Of the holes, thruſt through her Body with a Dagger in</l>
                  <l>Three places.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>What cheat was that you put upon the Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dev.</speaker>
                  <l>We Acted like Devils, and in a Song made him</l>
                  <l>Believe his Wife did Cuckold him.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:101837:36"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>This was <hi>Antonio,</hi> whom I met there, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devil.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, that's his Name, a mighty furious Man,</l>
                  <l>He ſaid, he'd kill e'm all before 'twas day.</l>
                  <l>He made me quake to hear him; I hope now,</l>
                  <l>Captain, you will let me go.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, you Rogue! If he has done more miſchief</l>
                  <l>You ſhall be hang'd, except you find your Fellows</l>
                  <l>That joyn'd i'th' cheat with you to make him Jealous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devil.</speaker>
                  <l>I'le bring you preſently to them, and ſhew you all</l>
                  <l>Their holes; they did but ſend me out to watch when</l>
                  <l>The Coaſt was clear!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Who, ſay you, ſet you on to this deſign?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Devil.</speaker>
                  <l>An ill-look'd Rogue, his Man, the Witches Nephew;</l>
                  <l>I think they call him <hi>Jaſper.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, take the Boy, and call ſome of your Fellows,</l>
                  <l>And there ſurprize them all: I'le not defer</l>
                  <l>My ſearching to prevent the miſchief</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Don Antonio</hi> further may deſign,</l>
                  <l>For I believe he had a hand in this</l>
                  <l>Was done i'th' Garden, however the miſtake</l>
                  <l>Did happen to begin between the Dead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, Sir, make haſte, for I begin to fear</l>
                  <l>Some Tragedy is Acted in the Houſe,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Don Antonio</hi>'s Rage is alwayes quick,</l>
                  <l>And they have toucht the ſtring will ſtretch it higheſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Come then, let's haſten back.</l>
                  <stage>Whiſtling behind the Stage.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, that's his whiſtle, and I muſt obey't.</l>
                  <l>Why <hi>Pedro, Pedro!</hi> What, are you dead aſleep?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro,</hi> I ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pedro within.</speaker>
                  <l>Who calls?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro,</hi> riſe quickly, my Lady <hi>Caelia</hi> wants you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>What can ſhe want me for at ſuch a time?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not, but <hi>Flora</hi> came, and ſaid you muſt</l>
                  <l>Come quickly, I think, to Ride to my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:101837:37"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I come, but I'le have a care of your Tricks, Nurſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>What tricks? What do you</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pedro <hi>in a Night-Gown, with his ſword in's hand.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Do with your Sword?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, Nurſe, you may have malice, and malice</l>
                  <l>May ſeek miſchief, which becauſe you are no Witch,</l>
                  <l>And cannot come through a Key-hole to compaſs,</l>
                  <l>For ought I know, you call me out to do it — ha!</l>
                  <l>What whiſtle's that?</l>
                  <stage>Whiſtle.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>What whiſtle! Are you mad! Go to my Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Still I ſuſpect you.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Nurſe, with</hi> Antonio <hi>and</hi> Jaſper.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Are they together, Nurſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, my Lord, the more's my ſorrow!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then, I ſee the Devils did ſpeak truth;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco,</hi> their kind Couzen, Whor'd them both,</l>
                  <l>By Heav'ns they took their turns, I ſee it plain!</l>
                  <l>O that I could invent ſome horrid Death,</l>
                  <l>And had but time to execute it on them;</l>
                  <l>But ſince I cannot, plain ſtabbing will do well,</l>
                  <l>The leſs they've here, the more they'l find in Hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope you will not kill your Lady, Sir!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Not kill her! But I muſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>What have I done? Oh, oh.</l>
                  <stage>Cryes out oh, oh.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, ſtop your mouth, I'le ſtop it for you elſe,</l>
                  <l>They'l hear her, and eſcape!</l>
                  <l>Come, <hi>Jaſper,</hi> are you ready?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, my Lord, I follow.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>What have I done, one Murder on another?</l>
                  <l>I ſee 'twas he that kill'd <hi>Eugenia,</hi> now,</l>
                  <l>By's naming <hi>Don Franciſco;</hi> oh, that
<hi>Jaſper</hi> —</l>
                  <l>Oh, the Ghoſt again — what ſhall I do?</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Caelia <hi>in Bed, and</hi> Flora <hi>all Bloody.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm ſorry that I ſent thee, ſince ſhe's mad,</l>
                  <l>But would 'twas day, that I might get her lookt to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm ſure ſhe has ſcratch't my face ſufficiently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis well it was no worſe.</l>
                  <stage>Pedro <hi>knocks.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas! ſhe'l come again!</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:101837:37"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flora, Flora.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>He knocks.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that, <hi>Pedro!</hi> What's the matter with you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Nurſe call'd, and ſaid my Lady would ſpeak with me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Bid him come in.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lady bids you enter.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pedro.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pedro,</hi> the Nurſe is mad, I did not call you,</l>
                  <l>You ſee how ſhe has ſcratcht poor <hi>Flora</hi>'s Face,</l>
                  <l>She came juſt now ſhreeking and ſtaring hither;</l>
                  <l>If you could lock her up into ſome Room,</l>
                  <l>It would do well.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>A noiſe, Exiturus, he fights, and Enters with</hi> Antonio, <hi>whom when he ſees, he lets fall his point, and is kill'd.</hi> Jaſper <hi>runs</hi> Flora <hi>through.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear her coming up.</l>
                  <l>Thieves, Madam, Thieves!</l>
                  <l>Oh Heav'ns, it is my Lord!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Damn'd Letcher, ſo it is!</l>
                  <l>What, does your Courage fail you —</l>
                  <l>There, take that —</l>
                  <stage>Runs him through.</stage>
                  <l>And boaſt in Hell that <hi>Don Antonio</hi>'s Sword</l>
                  <l>Did thee thr Honour to ſend thee thither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flor.</speaker>
                  <l>O Heav'ns! My fears were true, the Rogue has kill'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Monſter of thy Sex, ſee this, and tell me</l>
                  <stage>Falls &amp; dyes.</stage>
                  <l>What are the effects you do expect from it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>Death, that's leſs terrible then is your Anger,</l>
                  <l>Which I perceive by it's effects already,</l>
                  <l>Upon that Innocent Man cannot ſtay there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Are your concerns for him, when they ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Employ'd to Heav'n for mercy to your Soul?</l>
                  <l>Nay, then Hell take it's Quarry; this for <hi>Don Lewis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This for <hi>Don Franciſco;</hi> and take this laſt</l>
                  <l>For thy inſatiate Luſt with that damn'd Hind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>This killing me, my Lord, is very cruel;</l>
                  <l>Since I ne're ſinn'd in thought againſt your Honour.</l>
                  <l>This, as I do expect Eternal Reſt,</l>
                  <l>Is ſuch a Truth, that I can dye in it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>O Hell and Furies! This Womans impudence exceeds you all.</l>
                  <l>See there a Dog juſt wreeking from thy Bed,</l>
                  <l>Hot with the Labour you have put him to</l>
                  <l>And yet in thought you did not wrong my Honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:101837:38"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>From my Bed, my Lord! You are abus'd;</l>
                  <l>That fellow was not here full half a minute,</l>
                  <l>E're your ſelf enter'd! Oh, I can no more —</l>
                  <l>Heav'n and the World grant Pardon for my Blood.</l>
                  <l>For truth it ſelf bears witneſs; I dare ſay</l>
                  <l>That more I ſorrow for your guilt then Death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>If this be true, tell me as thou art dying,</l>
                  <l>What made him here at ſuch a time o' Night?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cael.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot tell more, then that the Nurſe did ſend him;</l>
                  <l>And ſhe's run mad with guilt, or ſhame, or both!</l>
                  <l>Oh, I can ſay no more — the Room turns Round;</l>
                  <l>My Lord, farewell — Heav'n pardon you all Blood,</l>
                  <l>As I forgive you mine — oh, oh, —</l>
                  <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Her Death both ſtaggers, and amazes me!</l>
                  <l>Are theſe Dead too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Not yet, my Lord, I am not.</l>
                  <l>Your Sword hath left me ſome ſmall time for Prayers,</l>
                  <l>And it had need; for I believe few Souls</l>
                  <l>Can be aſſur'd to find their way to heav'n</l>
                  <l>Without more warning to begin their Journey.</l>
                  <l>But yet I do not find much cauſe for doubt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, if thou'ſt hopes, by that I do conjure thee</l>
                  <l>Tell me, what brought thee hither?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>The Nurſes madneſs;</l>
                  <l>She call'd me from my Bed, and told me, <hi>Flora</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was ſent to bid me come unto my Lady,</l>
                  <l>Which though I ſcarce believ'd, yet I did do't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhy did you ſay it was her madneſs did it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lady ſaid ſhe was ſo, for ſhe came</l>
                  <l>Not long before ſhreeking into this Chamber,</l>
                  <l>So as you enter'd I was going down</l>
                  <l>To lock her up till morning in ſome Room:</l>
                  <l>This, as I hope for heav'n, my Lord, is true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Then 'tis as true, that I muſt never hope for it.</l>
                  <l>For I have kill'd a VVife of ſuch obedience —</l>
                  <l>But hold, I'le pump the Nurſe — who ſet her on</l>
                  <l>To tell me this.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe frighted.</stage>
               </sp>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:101837:38"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>O! whether will you drive me!</l>
                  <l>Be gone, be gone!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, here ſhe comes, I'le make her tell me all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>But I'le prevent the ſtory if I can. —</l>
                  <stage>Jaſper <hi>Runs Nurſe through but is ſtaid by</hi> Antonio.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>What, does the Villain mean to kill her yet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Does ſhe not deſerve it? To invent ſuch lyes,</l>
                  <l>And do ſuch miſchiefs with them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>O thou damn'd Rogue! 'Twas thou that made me do't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>You lying VVitch, be damn'd —</l>
                  <stage>Offers at her again.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Forbear, you Rogue, I'le do as much for you elſe.</l>
                  <l>Speak, why you did it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, he threaten'd me, and made me do't;</l>
                  <l>And taught me to call <hi>Pedro</hi> when you knockt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Look to your ſelf, my Lord, he'l kill you elſe.</l>
                  <stage>Jaſper <hi>runs</hi> Anto. <hi>behind.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>This way is only left — hell take your Tongue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah, thou haſt kill'd me; yet I have ſtrength enough</l>
                  <l>To ſend thy Soul to hell.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They fight. A noiſe without.</hi> Jaſper <hi>is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis done, I am catch'd at laſt in my</l>
                  <l>Own Trap. Oh, I deſerve my Death for want</l>
                  <l>Of fore-ſight, to let him Live a ſpye upon my Actions.</l>
                  <l>I ſhould have ſerv'd you thus, and thus,</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Runs</hi> Pedro <hi>through as he lyes, and Nurſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>And thus — and you too thus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, O, O!</l>
                  <stage>Pedro <hi>and Nurſe Dye.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Infernal Monſter! how his malice laſts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <l>This way's the noiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Captain, Watch, and Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat horrid ſight is this? VVe come too late.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Too late indeed, except you'd come to ſave</l>
                  <l>The beſt of VVives that there lyes murder'd</l>
                  <l>By my accurſed hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat, <hi>Caelia</hi> dead too! VVhat made you do't, my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas! he cannot tell; the Jealous fool</l>
                  <l>VVas but an Inſtrument in my Revenge;</l>
                  <l>'Tis only I can tell you why ſhe dy'd.</l>
                  <l>But yet I would not give that ſatisfaction,</l>
                  <l>Did I not fear my Name would be forgotten,</l>
                  <l>Except this Tale of my Revenge was known;</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:101837:39"/>
                  <l>In which I ſhall live famous. —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>O thou Dogg! Doſt glory in the miſcheifs thou haſt done?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>I, and have reaſon; name the man that ever</l>
                  <l>Did in one Day contrive ſo many Murders,</l>
                  <l>And make 'em all Succeſsful.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>But what ſhould move thee to this Villainy?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>For that you will not wonder.</l>
                  <l>I am <hi>Jaſper De Monſalvo,</hi> Heir to that Eſtate</l>
                  <l>This Lord doth now poſſeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah Heav'ns! ſome of that deſperate Bandity</l>
                  <l>Did once attempt my life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes truly —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Caelia,</hi> 'tis no wonder thy mind did boad</l>
                  <l>Great miſciefs from this Fellow, being Son of</l>
                  <l>One did ſtill contrive to kill me, for what the</l>
                  <l>King after juſt forfeiture for mighty ſervices</l>
                  <l>Had given my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>O Revenge!</l>
                  <l>Thy ſweetneſs takes away the taſte of Death.</l>
                  <l>But you'l loſe my ſtory; which in ſhort is this:</l>
                  <l>That Lady lov'd me not, and therefore I</l>
                  <l>Made her Lord Jealous, took him to a Witch,</l>
                  <l>And there I fool'd him finely: Till the Jade,</l>
                  <l>Who was my Aunt in deed, at your approach</l>
                  <l>Would have diſcover'd all; which I prevented,</l>
                  <l>And ſtopt her Mouth with this: Then I contriv'd</l>
                  <l>To kill <hi>Eugenia,</hi> knowing ſhe would meet</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco</hi> in the Garden; that I did</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſhe call'd me Villain, and refus'd</l>
                  <l>To lent me Whore her too, as did her Couzen;</l>
                  <l>And more, I knew the ſimple Lord I ſerv'd</l>
                  <l>When he had Murder'd her, as I ſhould make him,</l>
                  <l>Would thank my Care, and well reward it too:</l>
                  <l>Nay, I'd have him do't for his own ſafety,</l>
                  <l>That ſtill the Murder might be thought
<hi>Franciſco</hi>'s;</l>
                  <l>You know the reſt i'th' Garden. I taught beſides</l>
                  <l>That damn'd Old Hagg, whoſe fear has made me thus,</l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:101837:39"/>
                  <l>To put this trick on <hi>Pedro:</hi> I bid her call him</l>
                  <l>When ſhe ſhould hear us whiſtle, then in haſte,</l>
                  <l>And all undreſt ſend him to <hi>Caelia</hi>'s Chamber,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we, let in, might meet him coming thence,</l>
                  <l>Thinking the Cuckold's Rage would murder all,</l>
                  <l>And never hear 'em ſpeak; but there I fail'd,</l>
                  <l>Their dying words betray'd me, that's the worſt,</l>
                  <l>Or I had liv'd to glory in their Deaths;</l>
                  <l>But this my Comfort is, he'l not ſurvive me,</l>
                  <l>I have done his bus'neſs too before I dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Was er'e ſo Impudent a Villain ſeen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>I'le try to ſtop his wounds, that ſo</l>
                  <l>I may keep him for Execution.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand off, by Hell,</l>
                  <l>He that comes near me finds his Death with this!</l>
                  <l>Think you I'm grown ſo tame to dye by Law;</l>
                  <l>No, no, I'le not endure a formal Tryal,</l>
                  <l>To be upbraided with thoſe things I think</l>
                  <l>Deſerve a Trophy rather then Contempt,</l>
                  <l>Which ſince I know will follow, here's my Bail,</l>
                  <l>This will deliver any man from Jayl.</l>
                  <l>Let Cowards dye by hanging; ſuch as I</l>
                  <l>As we live bravely, thus dare bravely dye.</l>
                  <stage>Stabs himſelf.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>He has done well; no Excutioner</l>
                  <l>Could have been found ſo bad as his own hand,</l>
                  <l>And Hell will give him what he wants on Earth:</l>
                  <l>And yet, my Lord, it troubles me for you,</l>
                  <l>Since my Place binds me to ſecure your Perſon,</l>
                  <l>To anſwer Law for all your Rage has done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Shame almoſt ſtops my mouth; yet, Captain, know</l>
                  <l>My wound won't give me time for that misfortune;</l>
                  <l>Stay but a little, let me fix my Eyes</l>
                  <l>On what lies here, for that alone would give me</l>
                  <l>A ſudden Death, had I no other hurt.</l>
                  <l>I dare not hope for Heav'n, having done</l>
                  <l>So black a Murder on ſuch Innocence,</l>
                  <l>And yet I do believe her Charity</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:101837:40"/>
                  <l>As it did dying, ſtill doth beg that Pardon</l>
                  <l>Might from above be granted to my ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Which if I miſs, as I have cauſe to fear,</l>
                  <l>Then ſure I ſhall be turn'd into a Devil</l>
                  <l>For ever to Torment his Curſed ſoul</l>
                  <l>That led me to theſe miſchiefs.</l>
                  <l>'Twould be ſome eaſe, if Heaven but granted that,</l>
                  <l>But I begin to faint! Oh, Bleſſed Soul</l>
                  <l>Dart forth one Beam of Light, to guide the way,</l>
                  <l>Or I ſhall always wander in the dark.</l>
                  <l>Night ſeizes me already: yet from hence</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of death my ſoul ſhall take her flight,</l>
                  <l>Go where I will, I thus ſet out a right.</l>
                  <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Hes dead —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>By dying ſo, at leaſt he's thus far happy,</l>
                  <l>That he Eſcapes the Puniſhments of Tryal,</l>
                  <l>And the Exemplar death muſt have attended</l>
                  <l>Which to a man ſo Jealous of his Fame</l>
                  <l>As he was, would have been a Hell on Earth.</l>
                  <l>Your Duty to your Lord will keep you ſafe,</l>
                  <l>Yet you muſt to the Vice-Roy go with me</l>
                  <l>To be a Witneſs there of what hath happn'd,</l>
                  <l>The ſtory elſe will ſeem Incredible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ready, Sir, for all you ſhall Command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Jealouſie, thou ſickneſs of great ſouls,</l>
                  <l>To what a Rage didſt thou tranſport this Lord?</l>
                  <l>For had his Wife been falſe it was not good</l>
                  <l>By Murd'ring her to drown himſelf in Blood;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For Luſt may be Excus'd ſince fleſh is frail,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But Murder on the Soul does guilt Entail.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <p>The Curtain Falls.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:101837:40"/>
            <head>EPILOGUE</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>By Mr.</hi> Harris.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>A Tragedy, and not Heroick Verſe,</l>
               <l>The Comick part fit only for Farſe;</l>
               <l>No Atheiſm, nor any man we know</l>
               <l>Abus'd, no repartee, nor ſplendid ſhow;</l>
               <l>But very little Bawdy, and leſs wit,</l>
               <l>The Devil's in't, crys one, if this Play hit.</l>
               <l>Faith— may be not, and may be too it will,</l>
               <l>For Chance ſometimes exceeds all rules of skill.</l>
               <l>As he who Rageing did his Pencil throw,</l>
               <l>And Painted that by chance, he could not draw</l>
               <l>For we have ſeen, and lately too, a Play</l>
               <l>Cry'd down by thoſe that cannot keep away</l>
               <l>And when they come ſpight of themſelves they ſtay.</l>
               <l>And to our ſorrow we have others known,</l>
               <l>That for their wit have Wit it ſelf out-done,</l>
               <l>And yet you wits, that praiſe 'em ſeldom come.</l>
               <l>So the Goodman, oft-times for cauſe unknown,</l>
               <l>Leaves well-dreſt Beauteous Wife for Homely Joan.</l>
               <l>And you that Miſſes keep too, I'm afraid</l>
               <l>Do ſometimes make e'm Jealous of the Maid;</l>
               <l>So if this Play not dreſt by rules of Art</l>
               <l>Should with ſome Trick of Nature catch the heart;</l>
               <l>We'd give you leave to rail, and never fear,</l>
               <l>Becauſe we're ſure you'd come to do it here.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:101837:41"/>
               <l>Gallants you ſee what e're you ſay or do,</l>
               <l>Plays will be writ, and we ſhall Act 'em too.</l>
               <l>Some will for pleaſure, ſome for profit write,</l>
               <l>Some for Applauſe, and ſome will do't in ſpight,</l>
               <l>Such bit by Critticks, ſtrait run mad and bite.</l>
               <l>This does our bu'sneſs: but we'd have you know,</l>
               <l>VVe wiſh we'd none but true brisk wit to ſhow,</l>
               <l>VVe ſilence wiſh that Men might hear a Play,</l>
               <l>And wiſh that Vizard Mask would keep away:</l>
               <l>But we as well might wiſh we were thoſe Kings</l>
               <l>VVe ſometimes Act, as hope to ſee theſe things.</l>
               <l>Then ſince to rail o'th' Stage and in the Pit,</l>
               <l>Muſt in this ſickly Age be counted VVit;</l>
               <l>And that th' Infection connot be ſubdu'd,</l>
               <l>VVe Actors for our own ſakes do conclude,</l>
               <l>The Itch to write and rail will ne're be cur'd,</l>
               <l>And therefore faith let'em be both Endur'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 17. Line 36. For <hi>your</hi> read <hi>their.</hi> p. 23. l.
19. f. <hi>Taylors</hi> r. <hi>Juglers.</hi> p. 31. l. 18. r. <hi>my fears.</hi> p. 38. l. 7. r. <hi>Villain by.</hi> p. 51. l. 6. f.
<hi>firſt</hi> r. <hi>worſt.</hi> p. 53. l. 35. f. <hi>his</hi> r.
<hi>in.</hi> p. 57. l. 11. f. <hi>there</hi> r. <hi>then.</hi> p. 58. l. 36. f.
<hi>this</hi> r. <hi>his.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101837:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
